<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. John Bigg to which is added another sermon upon the same subject : also a narrative of Mr. Bigg's conversion, &amp;c. / by R. Davis ...</title>
            <author>Davis, Richard, 1658-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13106505</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13106505</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97516</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37260)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97516)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 413:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. John Bigg to which is added another sermon upon the same subject : also a narrative of Mr. Bigg's conversion, &amp;c. / by R. Davis ...</title>
                  <author>Davis, Richard, 1658-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[39] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Ponder,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bigg, John, d. 1691.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97516:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at the FUNERAL OF M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> John Bigg.</p>
            <p>To which is added, Another SERMON upon the ſame Subject.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A NARRATIVE of Mr. <hi>BIGG</hi>'s <hi>CONVERSION,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. DAVIS,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>ROBERT PONDER.</hi> MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97516:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97516:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>INſtead of an Epiſtle Dedicatory, I ſhall only briefly acquaint thee with the Reaſons that induced me to print theſe Sermons: and why they came forth ſo long after they were preached. I have ſometimes ceaſed to be a Friend to the Preſs, and never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to print them at all, though often put upon to do it: But the Lord, the Redeemer, whoſe Bleſſing and Power made Clay and Spittle to open the Eyes of the Blind, was pleaſed to own theſe ſo, as to make them of great uſe to ſeveral. Their Entreaty, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, prevailed with the Widdow of the Deceaſed, to impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune me further, ſo that her Importunity joyn'd with theirs obtained upon me, at leaſt to redeem (when I could) now and then a little time from the great Work of Christ, that is upon my Hands to ſet them in order, and ſo venture them into the World. There fell in alſo another cogent Motive, <hi>viz.</hi> The Conſideration of the falſe and lying Stories ſcattered through City and Country concerning me and the Doctrines I preach, made me willing to let all know (if they pleaſe to read) what thoſe Doctrines are, and ſo they may make a better Judgment afterwards. And I do aſſure thee theſe Sermons contain the chief Subſtance of what I preached here in the Country: Therefore I have made ſome Additions hereunto, and Alterations ſuitable to my main Scope in preaching this Year paſt. Had the Men of the World only caſt Dirt, it would have been more tolerable. Better could not have been expected from them, but to act accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Nature. But this has been piercing, that the Truths of Jeſus have been wounded in the Houſe of Friends. Here a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb facs="tcp:97516:3"/>Occaſion is given for a pathetick Lamentation; <hi>But tell it not in</hi> Gath, <hi>and publiſh it not in</hi> Askelon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> VVhatever Blows ſome aim at one another, they all fall upon their holy Profeſſion. whilſt a too eager Vindication is perſued of our good Names and Reputation from undue and unjuſt Calumnies, The Name of Jeſus and his Goſpel may be expoſed to greater Reproach. This made me chooſe to lie ſtill with a Gag in my Mouth, whilſt I was, and am ſtill cloathed with <hi>Sambanettoes,</hi> than uſe the Methods I might to aſſert my wronged Innocency, leaving it to God, the Judge of all, to vindicate his Name and Goſpel in his due time, and in his own way (which I am certain he will.) And as for me, let my Name lie in the Duſt, provided it may make for the Honour of Chriſt, and the Furtherance of his Goſpel. I am endeavourring to learn this Leſſon, to <hi>rejoyce in Reproaches</hi> (from whatever Tongues they come) as well as in <hi>Infirmities for Chriſt's Sake;</hi> and I would preſs after that meek Spirit of the Goſpel; that <hi>being defamed to intreat,</hi> viz. To intreat Chriſt on the Behalf of my Defamers, and entreat them in the Bowels of Mercy to lay aſide their Enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord Jeſus his Truths and VVays.</p>
            <p>Reader, I ſhall add no more, but <hi>commend thee to God and the Word of his Grace, which is not only able to tranſlate thee out of Darkneſs into the Kingdom of his dear Son; but alſo build thee up therein, and give thee an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance among them that are ſanctified. And now the God of Peace, that brought again from the Dead our Lord Jeſus, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the everlaſting Covenant, make thee perfect in every good Work to do his Will, working in thee that, that is well-pleaſing in his Sight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Glory for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97516:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL OF M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> BIGG, Gent.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 15.55, 56, 57.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>55.</hi> O Death, where is thy Sting? O Grave, where is thy Victory?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>56.</hi> The Sting of Death is Sin; and the Strength of Sin is the Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>57.</hi> But Thanks be to God, which giveth us the Victory thrô our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OUR Great Apoſtle in this Epiſtle of his, having anſwered ſeveral Caſes of Conſcience to the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> in this Chapter, refutes that dangerous Error, that denied the Reſurrection of the Dead.</p>
            <p>HE founds his Argument for the overthrow of the Error, and the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the contrary Truth, chiefly upon the Reſurrection of a buried Jeſus. Having proſecuted this from <hi>v.</hi> 12. with the Intermixture of other Mediums; and alſo exhortatory Inferences to <hi>v.</hi> 35. he there ſtates the Adverſary's Objection in theſe Words, <hi>With what body do they come again?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS Objection he anſwers ſhaving rebuked the Objector with the Title of a Fool, <hi>v.</hi> 26.) from the Nature of Grain thrown by the Sower into the Ground, riſing into a Crop of beautiful Corn, pleaſant to the eye and uſeful for food: Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhewing and explaining the difference between human Bodies and the Fleſh of Beaſts, Birds and Fiſh, and the difference of their Glory from the Terreſtrial and Coeleſtial Bodies, even the difference between Coeleſtial Bodies themſelves in Glory.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97516:4"/>
            <p>HAVING managed this, from <hi>v.</hi> 36, to 42<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he there applies it to the caſe in hand, ſhewing in <hi>v.</hi> 42, 43, 44. That the Bodies of the Saints are <hi>ſown in Corruption but raiſed in Incorruption. Sown in Honour, but raiſed in Glory,</hi> &amp;c. This he repeats, varying his Phraſe, <hi>v.</hi> 53, 54. And draws in this Inference in the Cloſe of the 54 <hi>v. Death is ſwallowed up in Victory;</hi> which Inference he confirms in a way of triumph, in the Words of my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Death, where is thy Sting?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>IN which words you have the Apoſtle triumphing in the Perſon of every dying Believer, wherein are contained theſe Parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. THE Apoſtles Triumph, in <hi>v.</hi> 55.</p>
            <p n="2">2. THE Cauſe of it. 1ſt. laid down negatively, <hi>v.</hi> 56. The Sting of the Believer's Death being pulled out by the Aboliſhing of Sin, which is <hi>Death's Sting;</hi> and the Reign of the Law over him, which is the <hi>Strength of Sin,</hi> poſitively laid down in <hi>v.</hi> 57. <hi>viz.</hi> A Victory being obtained over Death, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; which the Apoſtle mentions with Thankſgiving to the Almighty.</p>
            <p>IN handling theſe Words, I ſhall only inſiſt on the Triumph or Ovation in <hi>v.</hi> 55. and the rather becauſe the Proſecution of the Truth that ſhall ariſe from that Verſe, will reach and take in the chief Matter contained in the following Verſes.</p>
            <p>IN theſe words, you have, as was aforementioned, the Believer's Triumph over Death, and that in a twofold Reſpect. 1. In reſpect of his Soul. <hi>O Death, where is thy Sting?</hi> 2. In reſpect of his Body. <hi>O Grave, where is thy Victory?</hi> Without ſpending further time in opening the Words; they afford us this Doctrinal Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> THAT every true Believer, in the Moment of his Death, can Triumph over Death, and the Grave both in reference to his Soul and Body.</p>
            <p>I ſhall divide this general Doctrine into Two Branches, and ſpeak to each part. The Firſt is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THAT a Believer in the Moment of his Death can Triumph over Death in reference to his Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FIRST (as the Lord ſhall enable me) I will prove this Truth, and then explain and illuſtrate it.</p>
            <p>FOR Proof, I ſhall only at preſent give you two places of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Rev. 14.13. <hi>And I heard a Voice from Heaven, ſaying unto me, Write; Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord from henceforth: yea ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their Labours; and their Works do follow them.</hi> Where Firſt you have the Truth plainly aſſerted, —<hi>Bleſſed are the dead, that die in the Lord,</hi> or in dying in the Lord. 2ly, The Reaſons of it. 1. They reſt from their Labours. 2. Their Works follow them, <hi>i. e.</hi> They will meet with their Prayers and Duties entered on the File for their review as an additional to their eternal Delights. 3. You have here inſinuated the Certainty and Importance of this Truth. 1. The Commandment to write, they are weighty things uſually committed to Ink and Paper, and that for duration alſo.—<hi>Littera Scripta manet.</hi> 2. The Commander, the Spirit. I heard a <hi>Voice from Heaven, ſaying write,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>THE ſecond place is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4:19. <hi>There remaineth therefore a Reſt to the People of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97516:4"/>God.</hi> Their reſt is not in this World but in another; and they enter upon it in the moment of Death; therefore they have then ground of triumphing.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add to theſe the Experiences of Three Worthies. The firſt was <hi>David's,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Althô my Houſe be not ſo with God, yet he hath made with me an everlaſting Covenant, ordered in all things and ſure: For this is all my Salvation and all my Deſire; althô he make it not to grow. David</hi> was now on the brink of Eternity, taking a view of the paſt and preſent Diſorders of his Houſe and Heart, yet rejoyces and triumphs in the view of the Covenant of Grace, and his Intereſt in it, and the influence it had on the Eternity he was entring into. The ſecond was that of faithful <hi>Stephen,</hi> that glorious Proto-Martyr; who when the Stones that daſhed out his Brains and Life, flew about his Ears, cryed out triumphantly, <hi>Lord Jeſus, receive my Spirit,</hi> Acts 7.59.</p>
            <p>THE laſt I ſhall mention, is the Experience of the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 1.23. <hi>For I am in a ſtraight betwixt two, having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</hi> But very pat and pertinent to the purpoſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He being harraſſed with Labours, Perils and Sufferings, at the apprehenſion of the time of his departure being at hand, triumphs thus, <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>For we know that if our earthly Houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a Building of God, an Houſe not made with Hands, eternal in the Heavens:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HAVING thus, from the Holy Scriptures of Truth, proved the Doctrine, I ſhall proceed to the explication of it.</p>
            <p>'TIS undeniable, That Contraries do the better illuſtrate one another, as black Spots make a white Skin ſhine the brighter, and a Black-a-Moor, is a Foil to ſet off an <hi>European:</hi> Therefore I ſhall illuſtrate this Truth, by another Contrary, that I might the more emphatically explain it; which is this: The triumph of Death over an Unbeliever, and thus lay down the Doctrine to be explained.</p>
            <p>DEATH in Death triumphs over the Unbeliever, and the Believer triumphs over Death in dying.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with the firſt Branch, <hi>viz.</hi> Death in Death triumphs over the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believer; and (as the Spirit of the Lord ſhall aſſiſt me) ſhew you in what reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. DEATH triumphs over the Unbeliever's ſenſual Pleaſures. Where are now (ſays Death) your vain Pleaſures that you wantonly rolled your ſelf in, in your life time? What are become of thoſe jolly, merry frolickſom hours, that you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd away with your frothy Companions? Where are now your drunken Cups and Glaſſes, and your riotous Feaſts, with which you ſo often drowned and glutted your ſenſual Appetite? What do they profit you now? What pleaſure do you find now from your former repeated acts of Luſts and Beaſtlineſs? What reliſh now from thoſe brutiſh tickling of ſwiniſh Delights? What does all your vain Merriment avail you now? What fruit have you from thoſe Things, that formerly you reckoned your Heaven and Happineſs? Inſtead of Pleaſures, you now ſhall have your belly full of everlaſting Torments. Now your merry Moments are turned into an eternity of Sorrows. Now, inſtead of ſwimming in Wine, and luxuriouſly feeding on Dainties, you ſhall ſwim, world without end, in fiery Streams of burning Brimſtone. You ſhall drink your Tears, and feed on your own tortur'd Fleſh in endleſs and never-ceaſing Miſery. Now, the flame of your Luſt is ſucceeded by a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97516:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>hotter flame, even the flame of divine Vengeance. Now, inſtead of your frothy Spirit and vain Laughter, you ſhall have enough of howling, weeping and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Teeth. Nay, you ſhall carry with you all your Luſts and Corruptions to Hell, not to pleaſe you, but to pain you. The ſame Water that the Fiſh ſwims in with delight, if beated over the Fire, will be the Fiſh's torment.</p>
            <p>THE Sins you acted with pleaſure in the World, you ſhall act the ſame in great meaſure in Hell, but to your eternal torturing: You ſhall there act your Revenges, but wound none with its poiſon'd Arrows, but your own Soul. You ſhall there have your covetous Deſires enlarged, as wide as the Hell you are in; but it will only be your pain and puniſhment: Your own Luſts there ſhall be the Flames that will ſcorch you. Come thou, trembling Wretch, will Death ſay, to the place of ſinning and the place of puniſhment; and thy very ſinning ſhall be thy puniſhment. Oh! then will Death inſult in the words of the Wiſe-man, <hi>Whatſoever thine Eyes deſired, thou kepteſt not from them: Thou withheldeſt not thy Heart from any Joy,</hi> Eccleſ. 2.10. And now all will be <hi>Vanity and Vexation of Spirit to thee,</hi> part of <hi>v.</hi> 11. And alſo in thoſe Words as are written, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.19. <hi>Thou haſt long ſaid to thy Soul; Soul, take thine eaſe, eat, drink and be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rry, — But, thou Fool, I am come this Night to require thy Soul of thee,</hi> part of <hi>v.</hi> 20. And to add no more, Death will only change the Moods and Tenſes in that portion of holy Writ, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.9. inſulting thus; <hi>Thou haſt rejoyced, Oh! Young Man, in thy youth; and thy Heart has cheered thee in the days of thy youth; Thou haſt walked in the ways of thine heart, and in the ſight of thine Eyes; but know thou now, thou trembling Wretch, that for theſe things, I am ſent by the God of Juſtice, to bring thee into Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONSIDER this, thou voluptuous ſenſual Wretch, thou Drunkard, thou Belly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave, thou unclean Beaſt, thou Blaſphemer, thou Swearer, thou Reveller and Perſecuter, conſider this, and ponder it in thy Heart, thou muſt 'ere long come upon a Death-bed; this greiſly King of Terrors will ſtare thee in the Face. The Sting, that now at a diſtance thou ſeeſt not, when he comes near thee with open mouth, thou wilt then ſee and be diſmally affrighted at that fatal Fork. Death and thee muſt meet 'ere long, and thou knoweſt not but this diſmal meeting may be 'ere a week roles about, and how wilt thou like ſuch an horrid greeting, ſuch a black wellcome, ſuch a terrible language, and bitter inſultings as you have heard. How do you reliſh and ſavour thus being triumphed over in a dying moment. Oh! conſider this, and look out after the Remedy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. DEATH triumphs over the Pride of the Soul. The Pride of the Soul is either a Glorying before God, or a Glorying before Men. As it is a Glorying before God, I ſhall reſerve that to ſpeak to under it's proper Head, which is to follow. The Soul before Man prides in its Endowments, either outward or inward, Death will then thus Glory over their Glory. Where are now your aery Honour and bubble Dignities? What is become of your State and Grandeur? Where are now your Crowns, O Kings, your Scepters, O Princes, I have tumbled them in the Duſt, and my Spade has le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled them with the Earth. Could not your Purple, or your Fures, your Swords and Maces and Magiſtrates, defend you from my Arreſt? What ſignified all your Guards, your Officers and Attendance who would not protect you from me? What
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97516:5"/>a buſſel and fluſter have you made? How have you ſet all in a Flame about you, and waded through blood and ſlaughter, cruelty and oppreſſion, and all manner of villany to attain ſuch a Degree of Honour, and where is it now? My breath has blown it all away. Where is now O Spluttering Monarch, that great Conduct, that deep Policy, wherewith you conquered other Nations and enſlaved your own? What could you uſe none of it to avoid my Attacks? Where is that imperial frown that uſed to overawe the gaping, cringing croud; I have diveſted it of all Majeſty, and made it now meaner and ſimpler than the look of an <hi>Ideot,</hi> ſo ſays, the wiſeman. <hi>A Living Dog is better than a Dead Lyon,</hi> Eccl. 9.4. Thou cunning admired Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician in thy Neighbourhood; that madeſt all thy Neighbours tremble at thy fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Wit; that ſtudied'ſt only how to over-reach, cheat and impoveriſh, that thoughteſt to hook in all to thy ſelf? Why uſeſt thou not ſome of thy cunningneſs to deceive me too? Why didſt not thou play the Politician with me alſo? What do all thy Tricks and Artifices now advantage thee? Thou now perceiveſt that one <hi>event hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth to the Wiſe, and to the Fool,</hi> Eccl. 2.14, 15. <hi>As it happeneth to the Fool, ſo it happeneth to the Wiſe.</hi> Go now and try what all thy wiſdom and cunning will do in Hell? Conſider this you, that are Great and Honourable in the Earth. You that are cunning to deceive in your Neighbourhood, that admire and flatter your ſelf, that you can over-reach your Neighbours in bargaining. There will come an hour of Death; that will efface and tarniſh all the Glory of your Honours, Dignities, Wiſdom and Policies. There is no over-reaching Death. There is no ſuch thing as being too cunning for the Grave. Death will ſoon tumble down all the pageantry of your own Dignities and Abilities, that you have ſet up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n your own Conceit. The Fire of God's wrath will ſoon burn up your Cobweb Policy: <hi>For this your Wiſdom is your folly.</hi> Methinks this ſhould be as cold Water upon all burning Pride, and a check and rebuke to all your glorying, that very few of your Claſs and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion are choſen out to eternal Life. Your very Wiſdom, Parts and Dignities for the moſt part, mark you out for eternal Miſery. This is the Sum of what the Apoſtle Diſcourſes, 1 Cor. 26.27, 28, 29. <hi>For you ſee your calling, brethren, how that not many wiſe men after the fleſh: not many mighty, not many noble are called,</hi> &amp;c. read that portion of the Holy Spirit of Truth, conſider it ſeriouſly and tremble.</p>
            <p n="3">3. DEATH triumphs over the Riches and Poſſeſſions of a Man in ſuch Heart-rendring words as theſe. O where are now, Man, all thy vaſt Poſſeſſions? What ſignifie thy Heaps of Gold and Silver? Hadſt thee amaſſed together all the Treaſures of the <hi>Indies;</hi> they could not bribe me or buy me off. Eccles. 4.8. <hi>Thine eye has not been ſatisfied with riches in all thy life time.</hi> Now thou muſt carry none with thee to the Grave. <hi>Naked cameſt thou out of thy Mothers Womb, and naked ſhalt thou return thither.—Job.</hi> 1.21. Inſtead of thy many Fields, Farms and Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments now thou muſt be content with ſo much Ground as thy Body can meaſure out. Now inſtead of thy many Bags of Gold and Silver thou muſt reſt ſatisfied, to be wrapt up in groſſer Clay. Now farewel, gilded Coaches, fair Palaces, ſplendid and well Furniſhed Rooms, ſtately-Beds, and all other coſtly Furniture: Now for all the Numerous Troop of cringing attendants; thou ſhalt be ſurrounded with an Hoſt of Vermine, and for the very ſame end with the former attendants, to feed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97516:6"/>upon thee too. What is become of all thy Glory and Excellency now? 'tis all laid in the Duſt. Job. 20.6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Though thy excellency did mount up to the Heavens, and thy Head reach unto the Clouds. Yet, thou ſhalt periſh for ever, like thine own Dung: they which have ſeen thee, ſhall ſay; where is he? Thou ſhalt flye away as a Dream, and ſhalt not be found: Yea, thou ſhalt be chaſed away, as a Viſion of the Night. The Eye alſo which ſaw thee ſhall ſee thee no more; neither ſhall thy place any more behold thee,</hi> and v. 11. <hi>Thy Bones are full of the Sins of thy Youth, which ſhalt lye down with thee in the Duſt.</hi> Thus will Death then triumph.</p>
            <p>CONSIDER this, thou that forgeteſt God in the midſt of thy plenty and abundance, that notwithſtanding thy Pleaſures and Treaſures and great Poſſeſſions, thou muſt enter to eternity, poor and wretched, miſerable and naked, unleſs thou art cloathed with that Royal Robe of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs. No riches then will ſuffice to enrich thee, <hi>but the Gold tryed in the Fire, i. e.</hi> an intereſt in Jeſus; who was made the perfect Captain of Salvation through ſufferings. No Rayment will then ſo cover thee, as to hinder the <hi>Appearance of the ſhame of thy nakedneſs</hi> like that <hi>white Rayment,</hi> viz. <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God, which is of Faith.</hi> And without that Wedding Garment, thou wilt ſtand ſpeechleſs at the Bar of God, and then ſhalt <hi>be bound hand and foot, and caſt into utter darkneſs; where there is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> Mat. 22.13.</p>
            <p n="4">4. DEATH triumphs over a Man's own Righteouſneſs. Men are apt through the Horrid Pride of their Natures, to truſt to their own doings for Salvation; and 'tis but too too common for Sinners in a State of Nature to apply Plaiſters of their own making to the Smarting Wounds of their Conſciences, and to uſurp Chriſt's Royal Prerogative of ſpeaking Peace to their Souls; whereas, thus ſays the Lord, Iſa. 57.19. <hi>I create the Fruit of the Lips Peace; I ſpeak Peace to them, that are a afar off,</hi> viz. in a Natural State, <hi>and to them that are nigh,</hi> viz. them that are made, Eph. 2.13. <hi>nigh to my Father by my Blood.</hi> But over all ſuch white waſhed, painted Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, will inſulting Death Glory thus. Thou Phariſaical Fool, thou refuſedſt Fire from God's Altar, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord Jeſus, Joh. 5.40. <hi>Thou wouldſt not come to him, that thou mighteſt have Life;</hi> but thou haſt <hi>kindled a Fire of thine own;</hi> nay like <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> haſt brought <hi>ſtrange Fire.</hi> Iſa. 50.11. <hi>Thou haſt compaſſed thy ſelf about with ſparks. Thou haſt walked in the Light of thy Fire, and of the Sparks that thou haſt Kindled. This thou ſhalt have now at God's Hand by</hi> my Dart <hi>to lye down in</hi> a Bed <hi>of Eternal Sorrows.</hi> Thou wer't for digging to thy ſelf a Way to Heaven; and haſt refuſed the, Heb. 10.2. <hi>New and living way, that the</hi> God and Father of Chriſt had <hi>conſecrated;</hi> that is to ſay the <hi>Fleſh of Jeſus,</hi> or his <hi>ſuffering raiſed, glorified, human na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> and though, Iſa. 57.10. <hi>Thou waſt wearied in the greatneſs of thine own way;</hi> and haſt often tryed in vain with thine own Doings and Works of the Law, and couldeſt not; but in ſpight of thy Teeth, the Fire of Hell that was in thy Conſcience, would be often blazng-out, yet <hi>ſaideſt thou not, there is no hope;</hi> but wouldſt be ſtill hoping for Life from the Dead; unprofitable Works of the Law; <hi>Thus thou didſt ſind the Life of thine hands; therefore thou waſt not</hi> then <hi>grieved;</hi> but ſtill didſt ſtifle all thy convictions: But now thou ſhalt grieve, and eternally grieve without intermiſſion; now thou wilt not be able to ſtifle thy convictions, but they will tend and tear thy Soul with unſpeakable horrors for ever and ever.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97516:6"/>
            <p>NOW Pſa. 16.4. <hi>Thy Sorrous ſhall be multipled,</hi> that <hi>didſt haſten after other Gods,</hi> and other Idol Righteouſneſſes. Thou lefteſt no ſtone unturned, no way of working uneſſaied to procure warmth and life to thy Soul, Iſa. 57.5. <hi>Thou didſt enflame thy ſelf with Idols under every Green-Tree,</hi> and didſt let thy Heart run out for Holineſs and Salvation upon every Branch of, in it ſelf beautiful morality. Iſa. 57.6. <hi>Among the ſmooth Stones of the Stream was thy Portion, they were thy lot, even to them thou haſt procured a Drink-Offering,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> Thou haſt ſet up thy Duties for Saviours, haſt truſted in them, and ſo fallen down and Worſhipped them. Iſa. 57.7. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a Lofty and High Mountain haſt thou ſet thy Bed: Even thither wenteſt thou up to offer Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. i. e.</hi> Thou didſt confide in thy ſplendid towring Profeſſion, and didſt make a God and Saviour thereof,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 10. v. <hi>of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is a Key to open the the reſt of the Chapter.</hi>
               </note> by laying the whole ſtreſs of thy Soul upon thy outward Profeſſion, without Faith in Jeſus. Iſa. 57.8. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Doors alſo and the Poſts haſt thou ſet thy rememberance, i. e.</hi> And haſt ſet up a Record within thy ſelf for the Goodneſs of thy Eſtate from thy Family, and Cloſet Prayers; things good in themſelves, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Idols of Indignation, when advanced into the Room, and Throne of the Mediator. Iſa. 57.8. <hi>Thou haſt diſcovered thy ſelf to others, then</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>and art gone up;</hi> but <hi>thou wouldſt not come to Jeſus, that thou mighteſt have Life:</hi> What are now become of thy Doings, thy Works, and thy Righteouſneſs? Iſa. 57.12. <hi>I will declare thy Righteouſneſs and thy Works: for now they ſhall not profit thee.</hi> Cry now to thy Morality and Reformation; lift up thy ſuppliant hands to thy Duties and Profeſſion. Cry aloud to thy Prayers and Tears; thy convictions and thy terrors of Conſcience: Fall proſtrate to thy wiſhings, and to thy wouldings, and thy deſires to deſire to have thy Sin inwardly mortified under the obſtinate refuſals of Chriſt and his righteouſneſs. And try theſe thy Idol Saviours whether they will now hear thee. Iſa. 57.13. <hi>When thou cryeſt, let thy companies</hi> of Saviours <hi>deliver thee; but the wind now carries them all away, and vanity takes them.</hi> Hadſt thou truſted in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, thou <hi>ſhouldeſt now have,</hi> Iſa. 57.13. <hi>poſſeſſed the Land, and ſhouldeſt have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited his holy Mountain,</hi> even the everlaſting Hills in the Higheſt Heavens. But now thy Mountains of ſelf righteouſneſſes, which thou <hi>wenteſt up to, to offer Sacrifice to ſet thy Bed,</hi> and to <hi>build thy Neſts upon;</hi> and, which thou <hi>thoughteſt eternally ſtrong,</hi> I thraſh <hi>them to duſt,</hi> and <hi>my breath blows them away like chaſſ.</hi> All thy Phariſaical Doings, do now leave thee; and nothing of them goes with thee to Hell, but the unpleaſant rememberance thereof to torment thee, that thou waſt ſuch a Madman to ſet up theſe inſtead of Chriſt the only Saviour; as if thy good Duties, good Profeſſions, good Frames, and good Priviledges had undertook for thee from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity had obeyed the Law for thee with a God-like Obedience, and ſuffered the curſed death of the Croſs for thee, were raiſed up again, and by the Fathers right hand <hi>were exalted to be Princes and Saviours to give repentance and remiſſion of ſins,</hi> and were now ever living at the Fathers right hand to make interceſſion for thee. Why calleſt thou theſe <hi>good Saviours?</hi> There is none good in that ſenſe; <hi>but he that is God.</hi> Thus I ſay will Death then inſult in the dying moment, and glory over, and tread under foot like <hi>Dogs-meat,</hi> all the ragged Righteouſneſſes of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97516:7"/>
            <p>THEN conſider it ſeriouſly, thou, that with the Phariſee in the Goſpel, gloryeſt before the Lord, that thou art not as <hi>other Men, an Extortioner, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, an Adulterer, or even as the Publicans and Sinners,</hi> and layeſt hold on this for eternal Life. Thy Conſcience is not purged, but choked and bribed with falſe Counters, of outward Reformation. The <hi>unclean Spirit</hi> of Debauchery may be has been caſt out, and thou thinkeſt that enough; but the Spirit of the Lord, the Goſpel-ſanctifier has not been there at work; for he <hi>walked through dry places.</hi> The Reſt and Peace of Conſcience thou haſt obtained are not right; for 'tis written, <hi>he ſought for reſt, and found none.</hi> The Houſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> Thy Perſon has been <hi>ſwept</hi> by Reformation, and <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed</hi> with a fine Profeſſion: But 'tis but the ſtrong-hold of wicked Spirits ſtill. 'Tis <hi>empty</hi> of the Spirit of the Lord. The Holy Ghoſt has had no in-dwelling there at all; therefore the unclean debauch'd Spirit transformed into an Angel of Light, with <hi>ſeven other Spirits</hi> more <hi>wicked</hi> than himſelf (not more unclean than himſelf, but more wicked) a compleat Number of evil Spirits, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Devil of unbelief and ſpiritual Pride, two great Legions have <hi>returned</hi> and entered into thee; and if the Lord does not pity thee, and diſcover the rotteneſs of thine Eſtate to thee, <hi>Thy laſt ſtate will be worſe than the firſt.</hi> Ah! deluded <hi>Soul:</hi> Thou wouldſt heal thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience with thine own Medicines, thou wouldſt cover thy ſelf with thine own Righteouſneſs, thou wouldſt lay thy ſelf down on thine own <hi>Bed</hi> of eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs; thou wouldſt climb up to Heaven by thine own Methods, and find out a way for thy ſelf to eternal Glory. But thou will find in Death, thy Plaiſters will not ſtick, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Thy covering will be too narrow for thy Soul to wrap it ſelf in. Thy Bed too ſhort for it to ſtretch it ſelf upon;</hi> thy Ladder, unlike <hi>Jacobs,</hi> will not reach to Heaven. Thy own way to Glory, how fair ſoever a Proſpect it may have at firſt, does ſo wind and turn, that at laſt it will lead directly, <hi>down to the Chambers of eternal Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould have improved this Branch in ſeveral uſes; but having done ſomewhat of that under every Head, I ſhall only now anſwer a Queſtion, which I ſuppoſe ſome, if not many, may be ready to ask under the Conviction of their miſerable and loſt Eſtate by Nature. May be ſome, now under preſent awakenings, are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> WHAT ſhall I do to be ſaved?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer in the Words of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.31. <hi>Believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> WHAT, nothing elſe but believe on Chriſt? That I do already, and did it ever ſince I was born, and ſo do all, that are not <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. Firſt, They that ſay, they believed ever ſince they were born; never yet believed at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> FOR Faith grows not in Nature's Garden, neither is it born with us, <hi>But it is the Gift of God,</hi> Ehp. 2.8. and 'tis written, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. <hi>For unto you it is given on the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe on him,</hi> &amp;c. Whence obſerve, that to believe on the Lord Jeſus, muſt be given from above: Therefore 'tis not born with us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> THEY that think Believing an eaſy thing, I dare engage never yet believed. FOR,</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97516:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Nothing leſs than the Almighty Power of God in Chriſt, can work this Faith in us; even the ſame Power that created the World, muſt be put forth to an Act of Faith: 2 Cor. 4.6. <hi>God who commanded the Light to ſhine out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, viz.</hi> in the Creation of the World, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3. <hi>hath ſhined in our Hearts, to give the light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Whence obſerve, That to believe is to have a view of the Glory of the Eternal Godhead, eſpecially of the Glory of the Father's Grace and Goodneſs, ſhining through Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth.</hi> 2. That this Divine Beam of eternal Light, is infuſed into the Soul by the ſame powerful Command, that ſent down the creating Light to inform the dark Chaos: <hi>God who commanded Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c. Nay, a greater Power muſt be put forth to an Act of Faith, than to the World's Creation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the World's Creation there was no Oppoſition, though there was Indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; but in the ſinful Soul where Faith is wrought, there is Indiſpoſition and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 3. They that do not painfully feel the Evil of indwelling Unbelief, never knew what Faith meant. <hi>John</hi> 16.7, 8, 9, 10, 11. there when the Spirit is ſaid to <hi>convince</hi> of <hi>Judgment and of Righteouſneſs,</hi> he is ſaid to convince of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> too: And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Faith is, the contrary Principle of Unbelief riſes always to oppoſe it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15, to the end; <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.22, to the end, chiefly <hi>v.</hi> 29. where though the Apoſtle ſpeaks chiefly in both places of the contrary effects of the working Law and the working Goſpel, in the ſame enlightned Conſcience, yet the mutual oppoſition and warring of Faith and Unbelief, is alſo eſpecially included. I apprehend that to be a typical inſtance of this, ſpoke of to <hi>Rebeccas,</hi> Gen. 25.23. <hi>Two Nations are in thy Womb,</hi> &amp;c. This is evident, That no ſooner a grain of ſaving Faith is ſown in the Soul, but Unbelief, that afore lurked undiſcovered <hi>in the Soul, riſes inſtantly</hi> in Arms to war againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 4. They that are under no influence of the indwelling Spirit, have no Faith; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. Now <hi>if any Man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his;</hi> and he that is not in Chriſt, has not a drachm of Faith. They that have the Spirit, <hi>walk after the Spirit,</hi> v. 1. and are led by the Spirit, <hi>v.</hi> 14. they <hi>mind the things of the Spirit,</hi> v. 5. <hi>and their mortal Bodies are quickned, becauſe of the Spirit of Chriſt that dwelleth in them,</hi> v. 11. Now they that are never ſpiritually, <hi>but carnally min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> that know nothing what the indwelling of the Spirit means, nor his bleſſed Influences and Operations; but are ſo far from knowing all theſe, that they reproach and blaſpheme his bleſſed Perſon and Operations, as Whimſies, heat of Brain, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticiſm, Enthuſiaſm, and the like; how can it be ſaid, That ſuch Enemies of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit have the Spirit? And if they have not the Spirit, they are not only wholly ignorant of, but utter Enemies to the Grace <hi>of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 5. Dare the Drunkard, the Swearer, the Blaſphemer, the Sabbath-breaker, the prophane, ignorant, carnal, vile Perſon ſay he has Faith? His prophanity, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and wickedneſs always give him the Lye to his teeth, and his ſinful practice is an undoubted Teſt of the badneſs of his Faith, and that he profeſſes a Lye, when he profeſſes Faith in Jeſus. <hi>Shew me,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.18. <hi>thy Faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy Works,</hi> and <hi>I will ſhew thee my Faith by my Works. The Heart is purified by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97516:8"/>Faith,</hi> Acts 15.9. Nay, <hi>Faith ſanctifies throughout,</hi> Acts 26.18. Faith purifies the Converſation: 'Tis this <hi>Grace of God,</hi> this great Grace of Faith that <hi>teaches us, That denying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and worldly Luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, reghteouſly, nnd godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World,</hi> Tit. 2.11, 12. Nay, let me tell you, that ſuch have no more Faith in Chriſt, than Turks or Heathens: They have no more of Chriſt and his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, than the chiming of Words in their Heads, and the ſound of Phraſes rolling in their Memories: They have heard of one Jeſus Chriſt, and that is all; but they know him not. As to any Soul, Bellef and Conſcience, Perſuaſion, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, his pardoning Grace and his Righteouſneſs, they have as little as the very Heathens, that never heard of his Name: But they are worſe than the Heathens, becauſe they abuſe his holy Name, to patronize their Luſt and wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. BUT I can ſhew my Faith by my Works: I reform, hear, pray, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, weep, mourn for Sin, and profeſs: And have not I Faith then?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> THOU mayſt do all theſe, very commendable in themſelves, yet not growing on the root of Faith; and as truſted in, they are an abomination to the Lord. There is a vaſt difference between the Fruits of Holineſs flowing from Faith, and good Works ſet up inſtead of Chriſt the Object of Faith. Thou mayſt do all theſe, and much more, and yet make Saviours of them, and ſo be void of ſaving Faith, that looks to Jeſus, and him alone at God's Right Hand for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and at laſt be damned for idolizing thy good Works, as well as others are for wallowing in their Luſts: For all equally refuſe the Lord Jeſus, and will have none of him for Life and Salvation, but <hi>tread</hi> with, like ſcorn and contempt, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered <hi>Son of God under-foot:</hi> There's not a Dram of Goſpel-Holineſs, nor one Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical good Work, but what flows from Faith in the Perſon and Righteouſneſs of the once-crucified, but now aſcended, Jeſus at the Father's Right Hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. BUT for all my Reformation, Duties and Profeſſion, I ſeek to Chriſt too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> THAT is perhaps as the common Proverb runs, <hi>You will ſet the Cart before the Horſe.</hi> Your Duties and Righteouſneſs ſhall lead the Van, and Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs ſhall bring up the Reer. You will put him to no other uſe, than to carry the Train of your ragged Robes of Righteouſneſs, to patch up your Rags, and make up what is wanting in your Duties: But the Garment of Chriſt is ſeam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and cannot be divided; but if it could be, that <hi>his new Cloth could be pieced to your old, the rent in yours would be the worſe, Mat.</hi> 9.16. Perhaps you are ſenſible of your inability to do, therefore ye look to him for aſſiſtance to help you to do for Life: But what ſays the Lord, <hi>The Juſt ſhall live by Faith,</hi> Rom. 1.17. You would have him be King over you, to ſubdue your Iniquities, that for your ſubdued Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities you may get to Heaven. But you muſt look to him by Faith to be ſaved, and then mortification of Sin, and Holineſs ſhall be given in unto you. The High Prieſt under the Law had his Mitre and Crown on his Head, and his Urim and Thummim on his Breaſt, to typifie that the Lord Jeſus executes his Kingly and Prophetical Office, by his Prieſtly Office; and all whom he inſtructs and ſubdues, he does it by ſhedding in the Faith and Hope, either more or leſs, of their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned eſtate through his Blood into their Conſciences<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Again, Do not you ſeek
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97516:8"/>Chriſt becauſe of your Reformation, Duties and Tears? If ſo, you bring your own Money in your Hands to buy Chriſt; and that's quite contrary to the Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Lord makes of Heaven's Market, <hi>Iſa</hi> 55.1. <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth;</hi> that is, after the Things of the World, or their own Righteouſneſs; for 'tis ſuch thirſting as <hi>v.</hi> 2. calls <hi>ſpending Money for that which is not Bread, and labour for that which ſatisfieth not.</hi> Theſe are ſummoned here to come to the Fair of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where glorious Commodities are put to ſale, Waters, Wine and Milk. But what price muſt the Buyers bring? No price at all. They that would ſpeed in Heavens Market, muſt <hi>come without Money and without price,</hi> Heb. 12.13. Eſau <hi>ſought to buy Repentance with Tears, but he found no place for it.</hi> All buying in the meaning of Chriſt, is but accepting, and he gives the power to do that too: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come to Chriſt as poor, blind, miſerable, naked, vile, ungodly Wretches, and and he will be Riches to the Poor, Eyes to the Blind, Happineſs to the Miſerable, Cloathing to the Naked, and Sanctification to the Vile and Ungodly. The voice of the Goſpel is for the preſent time, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Now is the accepted time, behold now is the day of Salvation.</hi> Heb. 3.15. <hi>To day if ye will hear his voice, harden not your Hearts.</hi> The Goſpel does not ſay, Go home now, and pray, and mourn, and weep, and come to morrow, or next week, or next month, after you have prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and qualified your ſelf with ſo much praying, mourning, weeping, repenting and reformation, then come to Chriſt; but <hi>come now; now is the accepted time, now is the day and hour of Salvation.</hi> But, further, ſome may be ready to ask me,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHAT is believing in Chriſt, or Faith in him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> IT would be too tedious now to anſwer the Queſtion as it ought to be; I ſhall only briefly thus define it, and then make good my Definition. Faith, as ſtrictly and properly taken, is a powerful Conſcience-Perſwaſion wrought by God, concerning Chriſt and his Things, their excellency and ſuitableneſs to the Soul, and more or leſs concerning the Souls Intereſt in them, according to the Word of God. Faith, in the Original, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to perſwade, and really ſignifies a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading. 'Tis phraſed in Old Teſtament-language, in <hi>Noah</hi>'s Prophecy concerning his Children, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.17. <hi>God ſhall perſwade</hi> Japheth, <hi>and he ſhall dwell in the Tents of Shem.</hi> And to the ſame purport 'tis phraſed in the New Teſtament; 'tis ſaid to be, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. <hi>A light ſhining into a dark Heart;</hi> which is a perſwaſive Knowledge. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God in the Goſpel, revealed from Faith to Faith.</hi> 'Tis named, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21. a <hi>manifeſtation without the Law of the Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> v. 25. ſtiled <hi>a declaration of his Righteouſneſs for the remiſſion of Sins;</hi> and defined to be, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>The evidence of Things not ſeen,</hi> which are Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, which are wholly without us, not ſeen by our bodily Eyes, or natural Reaſon or Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. The Spirit in working Faith, is ſaid to take of Chriſt and his Things, and ſhew them to the Soul, <hi>John</hi> 11.14, 15. God the Father, as the Worker of it, ſo is ſaid to <hi>reveal his Son in</hi> the Soul, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16. Which Expreſſions evidently import a perſwaſive Knowledge. 2dly, This Perſwaſion is an inward Conſcience-Perſwaſion, and not only an Head Knowledge, or notional Perſwaſion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15. but <hi>when it pleaſed God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>to reveal his Son in me,</hi> &amp;c. 1 John 5.10. <hi>He that believeth hath the witneſs in himſelf;</hi> i. e. a Conſcience-Teſtimony. 3dly, This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience-Perſwaſion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97516:9"/>is very powerful, for it inſtantly works a great change on the whole Man, Heart, Lip and Life: 'Tis a creating Power, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. an exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great Power, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19. and 'tis the Declaration of the King of Heaven to the Conſcience; and <hi>where the Word of the King is, there is Power,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And (as Divines ſay) in this the Soul is wholly paſſive, like a dark Room, that has light let into it from without. The object of this Faith is Chriſt, and the Things of Chriſt, as in that fore mentioned place, <hi>John</hi> 16.14. <hi>He ſhall glorifie me, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſhall receive of mine, and ſhew it unto you,</hi> v. 15. <hi>All things that the Father hath are mine; therefore ſaid I, that he ſhall take of mine, and ſhew it unto you.</hi> The Rule of Faith is the written Word of God, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19, 20, 21. And this I take to be and Concomitants of this inward revelation of Jeſus, which are alſo called believing, which is the Souls accepting of this manifeſted Jeſus, and his Righteouſneſs, ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it ſelf upon him, and committing it ſelf to him; which Acts are ſet forth in Scripture by various phraſes; as, Looking unto him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.22. Coming unto him, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. Caſting our ſelves and burden upon him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.22. Staying upon him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.10. Leaning upon him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.3. Truſting in him, and many more. And thus I have anſwered this Queſtion with all the brevity and perſpecuity I could, as the Lord has enabled me, and as time would give leave. And now, methinks, ſome are ready to ask in the words of the blind Man, whom Chriſt had reſtored to his Sight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> BUT <hi>who is he that I might believe on him,</hi> John 9.36. You ſay he muſt be ſeen and ventured on; pray then who is he?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall anſwer you from the Sermons of the Apoſtles, preached by them after they were endued with Power from on high. And firſt the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells you who he is, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.22, 23. <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth, a Man approved of God; him being delivered by the determinate Counſel and Fore-knowledge of God ye have taken, and by wicked hands have crucified and ſtain,</hi> comp. with 32. <hi>This Jeſus hath God raiſed up, whereof we are all Witneſſes.</hi> 33. <hi>Therefore being by the right Hand of God exalted, hath received of the Father the Promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Once more, <hi>Acts.</hi> 5.30. <hi>The God of our Fathers hath raiſed up Jeſus, whom ye ſlew and hanged on a Tree,</hi> 31. <hi>Him hath God exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his right Hand to be a Prinee and a Saviour, for to give repentance to Iſrael, and remiſſion of ſins.</hi> Add to theſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Looking unto Jeſus the Author and Finiſher of our Faith, who for the joy ſet before him</hi> [in the ſaving of Sinners] <hi>enduring the Croſs, deſpiſing the ſhame, and is now ſet down at the right Hand of God.</hi> In ſhort, he that <hi>was made of the Seed of David according to the Fleſh</hi> (Rom. 3.) who <hi>yet is God over all bleſſed for ever,</hi> Rom. 10.5. That mighty glorious God-Man, who was born of a Virgin, that lived and preached in <hi>Judea, Rom</hi> 8.38. that <hi>died, yea rather that is riſen again, who is even at the right Hand of God, who alſo ever lives to make interceſſion</hi> (Col. 1.18.) <hi>the firſt born from the dead</hi> (Col. 1.15.) <hi>and the firſt born of every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> the deſpiſed <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> (1 Col. 2.9.) <hi>in whom the fulneſs of the Godhead dwells bodily:</hi> And all the Glory, Excellency, Beauty and Majeſty that ſhines on Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth.</hi> is the Glory, Excellency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Godhead. This is he, that bleſſed Object of your Faith; this is he whom you muſt believe in. When he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97516:9"/>lived on Earth, the Faith of his Children was more dark about his God-head than his human Nature, but now he is in Heaven, their Faith is more at a loſs about his human Nature, and it is to be lamented that the glorified human Nature, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> is ſo little in the Preaching, Profeſſion, Faith and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods own Children. But yet this is the Lord, whom we, through Grace, have ſeen and taſted to be gracious: Will not you too, O Sinners! come and taſte and ſee how gracious he is? <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.16. <hi>This is our Friend, this is our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, O Daughters of Jeruſalem.</hi> He is altogether lovely, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10. <hi>He is the chiefeſt among ten thouſand.</hi> He is able <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.27. <hi>to ſave you to the uttermoſt.</hi> O come therefore and venture your Souls upon him, commit them to him; O that you would but try him! you have tried his Patience to the utmoſt by your Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and Obſtinacy in Wickedneſs. O that you would but try his boundleſs Grace, by caſting your ſelves into the Ocean of it! You muſt venture on his Grace, or you muſt be damned. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that believeth ſhall be ſaved, he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth not ſhall be damned.</hi> If you accept not of this offered Jeſus, you deſpiſe <hi>this only Sacrifice, and there remaineth no more Sacrifice for ſin but a certain fearful looking for of Judgment and fiery Indignation, which ſhall devour the Adverſary,</hi> Heb. 10.26.</p>
            <p>I am now come to the ſecond Branch, the Believers triumphing over Death.</p>
            <p>AND 1. the Believer triumphs over the Sting of Death, and what elſe does concur to make it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. THE Believer triumphs over every thing elſe in Death that is formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> THE Believer triumphs over the Sting of Death. He then can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycingly cry out, O Death, I fear thee not! thou art very harmleſs unto me. Thou comeſt indeed like a Dragon, with open Mouth; but where is thy Sting? I dread not that open Mouth, or that wide Throat. I with Joy am ſwallowed up of it, and paſs through it up to the higheſt Heavens into my Redeemers Arms. Here at this dark Portal, I undreſs my ſelf of this mortal Fleſh, and fly with holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to the Preſence of the Lamb upon the Throne, and the Preſence of God the Father in him, and the bright <hi>innumerable Company above</hi> in this full Aſſurance, that I ſhall not be found naked. Wellcome Death, to diſſolve and pull down this earthly Houſe of my Tabernacle, that ſo I may go <hi>to my Houſe, not made with Hands, the Building of God, eternal in the Heavens,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. Wellcome ſweet Meſſenger, that comeſt to fetch me home from this mad, confuſed, wicked, raging, tottering World, into my Fathers Houſe. I thank thee, O grim Porter! who openeſt the Gates to eternal Happineſs. 'Tis true, the News of thy Approach did terrifie me, as the Report of the Coming of rough bluſtering <hi>Eſau,</hi> with his armed Men, did <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 32. But yet now thou art come to me, I can ſay as he did, I behold thy black and griſly Face, as the Face of the Angel of God, or the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. For in thy black Face I ſee Beauty, in thy griſly Terrors great Glory, In thy Dragons Mouth no Sting at all. <hi>O Death!
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97516:10"/>where is thy Sting?</hi> Thus the Believer in dying triumphs over the Sting of Death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. THE Believer in dying triumphs over thoſe things that go to make up the Sting of Death. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. OVER Sin. <hi>The Sting of Death is Sin,</hi> ſays the Words of my Text. And 1. In its Guilt. 2. in its Pollution. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. OVER the Guilt of Sin. Thus the Believer in dying glories over it: O Guilt of Sin! who in my Life-time, ſince my Converſion, notwithſtanding I was waſhed with the Blood of Jeſus, and he had obtained an eternal Redemption for me, didſt often uſe to ſting my Conſcience, and thereby to fill me with Dread and Horrour, and ſo didſt weaken my Faith and Confidence in the Lord Jeſus; didſt ſtrengthen the Hands of my Unbelief, in making me depart from the living God: Didſt make me often come in Prayer to God as my angry Judge, and not as to my Father, reconciled to me in Chriſt. And thereby didſt bind up my Soul, fetter my Spirits, ſo that I had no freedom of Acceſs to God through Chriſt: Thou didſt often deal with me as the Man that went from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Jericho;</hi> didſt wound me and ſtrip me, and leave me half dead: Didſt often force me to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain hard, murmuring and outragious Thoughts againſt my dear Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Jeſus, and my reconciled God and Father in him: Didſt often make me add Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to my Sin, and a carnal, looſe, vain Converſation to my inward Deadneſs and Enmity; and when Death approached to bring me to a State of perfection in Glory, didſt repreſent him to me as a dreadful King of Terrors. But now Death is come, and has executed his Office, I welcome him, and laugh thee to Scorn. Free Grace has diſarmed him of the Sting that thou wouldſt have given him againſt me. I ſhall now no more be perplexed with thy Gripes: I ſhall now plainly ſee my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption eternal, and always the ſame, without as much as a Cloud as big as a Mans Hand to interpoſe. I ſhall never look off the Lord, my Righteouſneſs, my Sanctification and Covering, but always behold my Fathers reconciled Face in the Face of my beloved Jeſus: I ſhall never depart from him any more: I ſhall now have perpetual Freedom and Enlargement of Soul before him: I ſhall never have an hard Thought of him any more, nor ever ſin the leaſt ſin againſt him any more. Farewell eternally, O Guilt of ſin! thou canſt not enter into Heaven, where I am going. Thus I ſpurn thee now, mounting up into everlaſting Glory.</p>
            <p>DEATH triumphs over the Pollution of ſin, and makes a full End of Corruption and Iniquity. Then may the Believer cry, O filthy ſink of Sin! thou ſhalt defile me no more. How often, even ſince Converſion, haſt thou raviſhed my Virgin Soul? How oftentimes a day haſt thou ſcattered thy Filth in my Conſcience, and left an envenom'd Taint there? How often, when I was going to approach an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, didſt thou appear in my Soul in thy ugly Colours, to terrify me, and to turn me aſide from the living God? Yea, and though I often ſaw the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt covering me, yet thou often filledſt my Conſcience with ſuch a Cloud of Filth and Stench, that that glorious Covering was hid from mine Eyes; but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97516:10"/>now thou ſhalt blind mine Eyes no more: I ſhall now have perfect uninterrupted Viſions of that ſpotleſs beauteous Garment wrapping me round, and that to all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. Not the leaſt ſpeck of thee ſhall enter into Heaven; in my Father's Houſe, I am entring into, there's nothing but compleat Purity and Holineſs: There is not the leaſt Atom of Dirt in the Streets of the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above. Here, thou filthy Load, I finally part with thee, I ſhall never be defiled any more with thee. Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah, <hi>Amen.</hi> And thus the Believer triumphs over Sin; that is the Subſtance of the Sting of Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> THE Believer triumphs over the Law, which the Words of my Text call the ſtrength of Sin; and the Law, or the Covenant of Works, is the ſtrength of ſin (though it be in it ſelf holy, juſt and good) in a twofold Reſpect. 1. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns the Soul, and tortures the Conſcience; ſo drives the Soul farther from God, and encreaſes the Enmity againſt him, and thereby puts the Soul more under the Power of ſin, enlarging and ſtrengthening ſins Dominion over it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Sin ſhall not have Dominion over you, for you are not under the Law, but under Grace.</hi> Where 'tis evidently implied to be under the Power of the Law, is to be under ſins Dominion; and this is exemplified and proved plainly and clearly in the former Part of the ſeventh of the <hi>Romans,</hi> which I cannot now ſtay to open. 2. The Law judicially delivers the Soul up to the Will and Power of ſin by way of Puniſhment. <hi>Thus the Son of God is ſaid to come in the Likeneſs of ſinful Fleſh, and for ſin, or ſinning, to condemn ſin in the Fleſh.</hi> Sin, by the condemning Law, has aſſigned it penally, as Executioner, a Power of ſinning in the Soul; from which Sentence, only a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Jeſus can free the Soul. The Law therefore as it is the ſtrength of ſin is a ſore Exerciſe to the Believer, and the ſtrength of the old Man, or the Body of Death in his Soul all his life time; but in his Death he may thus glory over it. Thou Covenant of Works, thou <hi>Killing Letter in</hi> my Conſcience, though I was much freed from thee by the Law of Righteouſneſs, which is of Faith, yet thou didſt ſtill work there, <hi>Gendring unto Bondage,</hi> oppoſing the <hi>law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Gal. 4.29. <hi>Thou that waſt born after the Fleſh, didſt perſecute that that was born after the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 4.30. <hi>But now the Bond-woman and her Son ſhall be quite caſt out.</hi> Thou didſt all my Life time endeavour all ways to keep up Guilt in my Conſcience, and if at any time removed, to do it away by Obedience to thee, by legal Sorrow and Contrition, by Reſolutions to amend, and greater Watchfulneſs for the future. Whilſt I was thereby diverted from making firſt Applications to the Blood of ſprinkling, ſo that my ſin was rather oftentimes compounded for, than in Faith waſht away, <hi>in that Fountain that is opened for Sin and for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs.</hi> Whence I was not only diverted from continual Believing into a bleeding Jeſus, but had my Conſcience rather ſtupified than healed, my ſin made little, harmleſs and familiar, and rather encouraged, than a real dying unto it, and hence often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times my Soul caſt into a deep Lethargy. But now I am abſolutely freed from that Yoak of Bondage <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> in my Conſcience, and ſhall be made for ever, to <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Stand faſt in that Liberty, wherewith the Son hath made me free indeed,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97516:11"/>John 8.36. Thus will the Believer in Death, triumph over the Law as it is the Strength of ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> THE Believer in Death may glory over the Juſtice of God, as it is armed with Vengeance againſt Sinners. Though Believers are fully delivered in their life time from the ſtroke of Divine Juſtice, yet they do oft times not ſo fully appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it: But after Death, the Believer ſhall <hi>ſee as he is ſeen, apprehend as he is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended;</hi> and then be enabled to rejoyce thus. Divine Juſtice, whilſt I lived, though thou waſt my Friend in Jeſus, yet many times I dreaded thee as mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; but now I plainly ſee thou art my Friend indeed, and that it is <hi>juſt with thee to juſtifie me</hi> in <hi>the Lord, my Righteouſneſs.</hi> Thy Sword that was pointed at my Breaſt, and ſhould have now thruſt me down to Hell, was received by my cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Lord into his own Bowels, and I am now made for ever to eſcape, <hi>Being made more than a Conqueror through him that loved me.</hi> My dying Saviour in Falling, wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy Weapon out of thy Hand, and made his bleſſed Body a Grove, planted from thy poiſonous Quiver, ſo that there is not an Arrow now left to ſpend upon me. I now come, O Juſtice, in the Right of my Lord, to ſit for ever down in his heavenly Manſions; to ſing Hallelujahs to that righteous and true God for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> THE Believer in Death may triumph over Satan. Satan, though a Soul is Tranſlated out of his Kingdom, yet through his reſtleſs Enmity, is always ſeeking to devour. He has <hi>Wiles Methods,</hi> and <hi>cunning Devices</hi> of Temptations to enſnare; imperious Suggeſtions, fierce Aſſaults, and fiery Darts to terrifie: with theſe ſeveral ways of Attacks is the poor Believer harraſſed as long as he lives; but in Death he can inſult over all. Thus then can the Believer vaunt it: Satan, thou haſt long tortured me with throwing in wicked and blaſphemous Suggeſtions, and then perſwadedſt me, to my great Terrour, I had ſinned the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt. Thou ſhalt no longer be able to throw in any more of thy fiery Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations. I am now beyond the reach of any of thy Darts. Thou haſt always endeavoured to tempt me to ſin, and then to make me queſtion my Intereſt: But now I ſhall ſin no more, nor queſtion my Intereſt any longer. I ſhall not now be tempted any more to Deſpair on the one hand, nor preſume on the other. Thou dareſt not appear where I am going. Thou vile Satan, I ſhall be diſturbed with thee no longer. I ſhall have no further Concerns with thee, till I come with my Lord to ſit in Judgment upon thee at the great Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly, and laſtly,</hi> THE Believer can thus triumph over the World, which is the laſt thing that goes to make up the Sting of Death. Thou empty confuſed World, that didſt uſe to terrify me with thy Threats, I defy thee and them now; and waſt wont to allure me with thy Flatteries: I am above their Undermining now. I ſcorn thy Rattles, and thy painted Beads, and thy airy Bubbles. I dread not now thy haggard Face; nor ſhall I any more be moved with thine Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97516:11"/>It will add to my Pleaſure in my Manſions of Glory, to ſee thee burnt for thy Witchcraft; I ſhall no more dread thy mighty Hunters, nor be aw'd with thy grim Tyrants, nor be enſlaved in Body, nor Conſcience, by thy bloody Laws, now be harraſed with brutiſh Executioners. There are no oppreſſing Magiſtrates, no Catch-poles, nor Informers in the place I now enter to. Nay, now I tread un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot all in thee, that is enticing; I ſet Health, Wealth, Pleaſures, Honours, Friends, Relations and all in one Scale, and my dear Fore-runner in the other, and that Scale weighs down now to the Ground. I now go to the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that better Country, where I ſhall have better Riches, and more durable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, better Honours, better Pleaſures, and far better Relations. Thus will the Believer then triumph over Death, and whatſoever goes to make up the Sting of it.</p>
            <p>BUT <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Believer can triumph over every thing elſe in Death, that is formidable. To inſtance in one for many, Nature abhors a Diſſolution, and the Soul, though it has but a bad Lodging, does not care to be turned out of Doors. Its tenement of Clay it cares not to be diſlodged of, though its all over tattered, and needs Repairs. It ſhrinks back at entring into a new way of acting ſeparate from the Body, when it has all the while been accuſtomed to act only by ſuch an Organ. It has been uſed to ſuch a poor Garment, yet as ſorry as it is, it knows not how to be undreſſed of it, and made naked. Whereas now in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Death, that's over to the Believer: It can cry then like his Maſter giving up the Ghoſt, <hi>All is finiſhed.</hi> It ſees a better Houſe to go to, upon its being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed of this, even the Fathers Houſe, that has many Manſions. And a better Garment to be cloathed with, even his elder Brother's glorious Robe of curious Embroidery: And can triumph in the Words of the Apoſtle, varying a little the Form of ſpeaking, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I now ſee <hi>that my earthly Houſe of this Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle being diſſolved, I have a Building of God, an Houſe not made with Hands, eternal in the Heavens. In this I have groaned, earneſtly deſiring to be cloathed upon with my Houſe which is from Heaven.</hi> I am ſure, <hi>being ſo cloathed, I ſhall not be found naked.</hi> For I, <hi>that in this Tabernacle did groan, being burdened,</hi> not for <hi>that I would be uncloathed, but cloathed upon.</hi> And <hi>now Mortality ſhall be ſwallowed up of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THUS the Believer triumphs over this Terror of Death, and every thing elſe in Death that is terrible. And thus I have finiſhed the firſt Branch of my Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Believer, in Death, triumphs over Death, in reference to his Soul. I ſhould paſs away now to various Uſes, but time will not permit; I ſhall therefore wind up this Branch with one Word of Exhortation to poor Sinners.</p>
            <p>O you poor periſhing Sinners, over whom my Bowels yearn! In my Maſter's Name I beg, that you would ſuffer a Word of Exhortation. You muſt needs be all perſwaded firmly of this, that you muſt once die, and you know not how ſoon: You may perhaps go to bed well, and never ſee Morning. Would you then in that inſtant of time avoid being inſulted over by Death, and triumph over that cruel Dragon, Death and his fatal Sting; then look up to that brazen Serpent, the bleſſed Jeſus, erected on the Pole of Gods Word, the only Hope, <hi>ſet before you in the Goſpel.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97516:12"/>O fly to it for Refuge! Would you glory over that King of Terrors, and all his Dread, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Be ſtrong in the Grace that is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Would you <hi>die the Death of the Righteous; then you muſt live the Life of the Righteous;</hi> and we are told what that is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>The Juſt ſhall live by Faith.</hi> Believe in the Lord Jeſus, the exalted Prince and Saviour, and his God-like Righteouſneſs; and earneſtly beg of the Lord for the <hi>Revelation of the Righteouſneſs of God to you from Faith to Faith,</hi> Rom. 1.17. That ſo when that Faith is going to be ſwallowed up of Viſion, you may triumph over Death and all its Terrors, in reſpect of your precious and immortal Soul.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97516:12"/>
            <head>The Second SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 15.55.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>O Grave! Where is thy Victory.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SOME of you may remember, that from the Words opened and Explained, I raiſed this general Obſervation.</p>
            <p>THAT every true Believer, in the Moment of his Death, can triumph over Death and the Grave, as well in reference to his Soul as to his Body.</p>
            <p>I divided it into two Branches; the firſt whereof was this. That a Believer in the Moment of his Death, can triumph over Death in reſpect of his Soul, which I have diſpatched, and now proceed to handle the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THAT a Believer in Death can triumph over the Grave, in reſpect of his Body.</p>
            <p>I judge it moſt convenient to uſe the ſame Method in the Proſecution of this Branch, as I did in the former, <hi>viz.</hi> to illuſtrate it by its contrary; and therefore lay it down thus to be ſpoken to.</p>
            <p>THE Grave can triumph over the Unbelievers Body; but the Believer can triumph over the Grave in reſpect of his Body.</p>
            <p>SINNERS are apt to make Gods of their Bodies, honouring them exceſſively with Food, Rayment, Lodging, and the like; and to glory in the Health, Beauty and Strength of their Bodies; but the Grave will trample upon all theſe. Inſtead of delicious Wine, and choice Dainties, the Grave will fill their Mouths and Bellies with Duſt: Their Silks, and Laces, and abominable impudent whoriſh Head dreſſes, their proud and lofty Creſts ſhall be exchanged for ſtinking Rottenneſs, odious Filth, and crawling Maggots. And inſtead of their ſtately Houſes and Down Beds, they muſt be content to take up with a dark Hole, and a cold Bed of Clay. The moſt vigorous Health then is vaniſhed; a little pitiful Vermine can there deal with the ſtouteſt <hi>Hector,</hi> and the ſtrongeſt <hi>Sampſon.</hi> The faireſt Face will ſoon prove as diſmal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97516:13"/>there as the fouleſt Monſter. The moſt exquiſite Beauty look as ſquallid, and as horrid as the uglieſt Blackamoor; and none ſhall be able to ſee any Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the rotten Skull of the one and the other. But having ſpoken ſomewhat to theſe things already, and being deſirous to haſten to other Matter, I ſhall here put a Concluſion to this, and only add three or four things to be conſidered in. Death, wherein Death and the Grave triumphs over a Sinners Body, but the Believer tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umps over Death and the Grave, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall ſpeak to both the Contraries together by way of <hi>Antitheſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. NATURAL Death to the Wicked is an entrance to eternal Death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. <hi>And 'tis appointed to Men once to die, but after this, the Judgment.</hi> The Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law of God has ſo ordered it for Sinners, that Death, as a Sergeant ſhall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and caſt their Bodies to the Grave as to a Dungeon, there to be reſerved in Deaths Chains to the Judgment of the great Day. But natural Death to the Godly is a Paſſage to eternal Glory: and Death, like a skilful Chymiſt, takes their Bodies and puts them into the Alembick of the Grave, and there diſtils them into pure ſpiritual and glorious Bodies againſt the great Day; but more of this hereafter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. NATURAL Death to the Wicked, is a part of the penal Sentence of the Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. — <hi>For in the Day that thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die.</hi> The Law threatned a threefold Death, ſpiritual, temporal and eternal. The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiſm in the Original is emphatical to the Purpoſe, <hi>dying thou ſhalt die.</hi> To me having this Force dying in thy Body, thou ſhalt die eternally in thy Soul. 'Tis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that to the Ungodly, natural Death is a part of that puniſhment inflicted by the righteous Law of God; and what Death is, the Grave is the ſame. If one be the Laws Jaylor to the Body, the other is the Laws Priſon. But to the Godly 'tis far otherwiſe: For as Death has loſt his Sting to them, ſo has the Grave: 'Tis not to them penal, but purely natural; the putting off the old <hi>Adam,</hi> that the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> may take poſſeſſion of the whole Body. The Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. diſcourſing of the Neceſſity of the natural Death of Believers, argues thus, That the old <hi>Adam</hi> had firſt took poſſeſſion of the Elect Veſſels Bodies. <hi>V.</hi> 46. That what of the old <hi>Adam</hi> is there, is earthly, and tends to Earth and Diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>V.</hi> 47. It being the proper Nature thereof. <hi>V.</hi> 48. Concludes thus, that the Image of the old <hi>Adam</hi> on the Body muſt be wholly laid aſide, and that by Death; ſo that the Image of the ſecond might take ſole and full Poſſeſſion. <hi>V.</hi> 49. <hi>As we have born the Image of the Earthy, we ſhall alſo bear the Image of the Heavenly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. NATURAL Death is a ſeparation of the Body from all Life; and thus it is to the Wicked: Their Duſt dwell alone in the Grave, united to nothing, only there reſerved by an Almighty Power of God, in an extraordinary way, for the Glory of his Juſtice hereafter. But the Duſt of the Godly in their Graves, are united to the Body of Chriſt now in Heaven, and there is held ſtill a ſecret Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence between their ſcattered Duſt and the Life of Jeſus, who in this ſence, is the <hi>Reſurrection and the Life.</hi> To make this more evident, 'tis to be conſidered, 1. That the Perſon of the Believer, both Body and Soul, in the firſt act of Faith, is united to the Perſon of Chriſt; yea, joyned to the Body of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. 2. That by vertue of this Union, the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> takes Poſſeſſion of the Body as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97516:13"/>well as the Soul, as proved afore from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45, to 50. eſpecially 46. <hi>Howbeit, that was not firſt which is ſpiritual; but that which is natural, and afterward ſpiritual.</hi> Obſerve that the Apoſtles Diſcourſe muſt be here confined to the Bodies of the Saints, for it is the Reſurrection of their Bodies he is a proving. 3. The Believer holds his natural Life upon another tenure than he did formerly, even from the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> by vertue of his Implantation into him. The great Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. declaring how his Body had been ſupported in the Work of Chriſt, under all Perils, Pains, Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Labours, Impriſonments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> almoſt inſupportable, declares the Cauſe <hi>V.</hi> 10. That it was from the Life of Jeſus made manifeſt in his Body, repeating the ſame in the laſt Clauſe of the 11th. <hi>Verſe,</hi> only inſtead of Body, there he writes <hi>mortal Fleſh:</hi> All which thus explained, does evidently prove, that the Bodies of the Saints derive now their natural Life in great meaſure from another Root. 4. As an unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable Conſequence of this, that that Life the Body holds from Chriſt, does not quite vaniſh, as that of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> does; but is gathered up into Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats back to him the Root, as the Sap of Trees in Winter Time falls down from the Branches to the Root. And I take that to be the Meaning of that place of holy Writ; or at leaſt I may allude to it, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Your Life is hid with Chriſt in God,</hi> eſpecially becauſe of the following Verſe, <hi>when Chriſt, who is our Life, ſhall appear, then ſhall ye alſo appear with him in Glory;</hi> which Glory reſpects the Body as well as the Soul. 'Tis to me plain that there is a ſecret Commerce between the Living glorious Body of an exalted Jeſus, and the Duſt of a deceaſed Believer, which may be further proved from <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.31, 32. The Argument Chriſt himſelf uſes to prove the Reſurrection of the Dead, and the force of his Argument I apprehend to lye here: That God calls himſelf the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> though dead: That God is not the God of the Dead, but of the Living, therefore, that though <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> &amp;c. were dead, yet they were ſtill united to the living God, and by Vertue of thoſe ſecret Beams of Life from him (the inſeparable Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of that Union) that ſtill correſponded and preſerved their mouldered Bodies in the Grave, they ſhould be raiſed up at the laſt Day. This ſence of the Place ſeems to be confirmed from the Anſwer of our Lord Jeſus to <hi>Martha</hi>'s Objection againſt the preſent Reſurrection of her Brother, <hi>John</hi> 11.34. Martha <hi>ſaith unto him, I know that he ſhall riſe again in the Reſurrection at the laſt day.</hi> John 35. <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto her, I am the Reſurrection and the Life,</hi> &amp;c. As if he ſhould have ſaid, thou grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that I can raiſe him up at the laſt Day; but how? Is it not by Vertue of that Union that is between his dead Body, and my living Body? If then I will be his Life, and therefore his Reſurrection. I am now his Life, and conſequently can be now his Reſurrection. I ſhall add that Argument, the Lord, the Holy Ghoſt, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Life abides and dwells in a Believer for ever, in his Body as well as his Soul. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. <hi>What, know ye not that your Body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, which is in you,</hi> &amp;c. If it be granted then, that he does ſtill indwell in the ſeparate Soul of the Believer, why not in a ſenſe in the ſeparate Body too? He brooded formerly over the Chaos till it was formed into a beautiful Creation; and why not in like manner over the Duſt, till the appointed time of actual Life by the Father comes? but,</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97516:14"/>4. NATURAL Death tends to an utter Abolition. Natural Death in it ſelf, tends to an utter Conſumption of the Body, and that by Steps retrograde to the Methods of the firſt Creation. <hi>Firſt,</hi> There was a Chaos created, and then that diſpoſed and diſgeſted into a very beautiful and lovely Frame; but Death deals thus with Man, the Epitome of the Creation, reduces the fair Structure to a Chaos, or Heap of Duſt, and then commits it to the Grave to annihilate it. And ſo would the Bodies of Sinners be annihilated, eſpecially in the univerſal Conflagration; but that, as has been afore mentioned, the God of Nature by his infinite Power preſerves and ſits them to be Veſſels of Wrath for Deſtruction, and at laſt raiſes them, that they might be for ever miſerable Companions to their miſerable Souls, on which he might make the Power of his Vengeance known to all Eternity. That as the Body has been a a Companion to the Soul in ſinning, ſo it ſhall be World without end, in ſuffering. But as to the Bodies of the Saints, it is otherwiſe. Death only ſows their Bodies into the Ground, that they might be quickned again into more glorious Bodies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.36, 37. compare with 42, 43. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And pulls down the old tottering Houſe, that it may be built up a more glorious Fabrick in the Day of Reſurrection, and they ſhall ariſe then from the refining Alembick of the Grave, with ſeveral wonderful Advantages; eſpecially theſe five,</p>
            <p n="1">1. THEN Corruptibility ſhall put on Incorruptibility, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.53. For this <hi>Corruptible muſt put on Incorruption,</hi> and when thrown into the Grave corruptible Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies then ſhall be raiſed incorruptible—<hi>V.</hi> 42. <hi>Sown in Corruption, raiſed in Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</hi> The Bodies of the Saints ſhall have no tendency to decay any more; no more ſhall the Bodies of the Wicked: but here will be the Difference; the Bodies of the Saints will be unpaſſible, and will not be capable of ſuffering Pains; but the Bodies of the Wicked, though not apt to decay, yet will be the Seat of eternal Pains and Torments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Then Immortal ſhall put on Immortality,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.53, 54. And the Bodies of the Saints ſown mortal, ſhall riſe immortal. There will be no dying in the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above, nor decaying, nor fading; but Bodies as well as the Spirits of the Juſt being made perfect, ſhall endure the ſame in that glorious State to all Eternity. 'Tis true, the Bodies of Unbelievers ſhall never die more; but their Living and Continuing will be a conſtant Dying. They will be dying to all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, but never abſolutely die; and happy would it be for them, if they could altogether ceaſe to be. But on the Bodies of Believers, the ſecond Death can have no Power at all. As for inſtance, <hi>The laſt Enemy that Chriſt will deſtroy for them, will be Death,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.26. <hi>And then Death will be ſwallowed up in Victory,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.54.</p>
            <p n="3">3. THEN natural Fleſh will put on Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44. <hi>It is ſown a natural Body, it is raiſed a ſpiritual Body. There is a natural Body, and there is a ſpiritual Body.</hi> Not that theſe natural Bodies in the Saints ſhall be turned into the very Eſſence of Spirits; but they ſhall come as near their Natures as 'tis poſſible, for corporeal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to come. So ſays our Lord himſelf, in anſwer to the <hi>Sadduces</hi> Cavil, <hi>Mat:</hi> 22.30. <hi>For in the Reſurrection, they neither marry, nor are given in Marriage; but are as the Angels of God in Heaven.</hi> i. e. They ſhall be as near to the Nature of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97516:14"/>as is poſſible. They will be of a purer and more incompound Subſtance, than the pureſt Elements of Fire: They will be endued then with wonderful agility and celerity, and their motion ſurpaſſing ſwift; probably they will fly then as ſwift as Thoughts: We experience that our Thoughts now ſpeed in an inſtant to the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermoſt Regions of the Earth, whilſt the heavy Log of a Body ſtays behind, and can go no faſter than its Legs can carry it, or ſome more artificial means. But doubtleſs then our Bodies, that believe will be fitted to keep pace with our glorified Souls, in all their Motions, for the Glory of God in Chriſt, not hindred by Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and Ails, nor made ſlow with any weakneſs, imperfection, or mutilation. The Sun is ſwift in his race; but what is his race compared to that of the glorified Bodies of the Saints then!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> DISHONOUR then will put on Honour, and <hi>that that is ſown in Diſhonour will be raiſed in Glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.43. Then they will be in part clothed with the Glory that is upon the Body of an exalted Jeſus. 'Tis true, there will be difference in degrees, though not in kind: <hi>For as there is one Glory of the Sun, another Glory of the Moon; and another Glory of the Stars: For one Star differeth from another Star in Glory.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.41. So the Glory on the Body of Chriſt, will be as the Glory of the Sun; and the Glory of the Bodies of his Children like the Glory of the Stars, all ſhining in Brightneſs, Splendour and Majeſty, though not equally alike. When Chriſt appeared with <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> in the Transfiguration on the Mount, the Glory then on his Body is ſet forth, as in a Glaſs: <hi>His Face did ſhine as the Sun, and his Rayment was white as the Light,</hi> Mat. 17.2. So will the riſen Bodies of the Saints be, ſhining brighter than the Sun, whiter than the pureſt Light. That, that is ſown in Diſhonour, as afore hinted, will be raiſed in Glory. They that are laid in the Earth little Infants, will be raiſed in full growth and perfect ſtature<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; they that be entombed decrepit, old and deformed, ſhall riſe again well-ſhaped, vigorous and beautiful. They that drop to the Grave poor, tattered, Servants and Slaves, ſhall come out from thence rich, free and illuſtrious, greater than Kings and Emperours: Then indeed in a literal ſenſe the <hi>Eyes of the Blind ſhall be opened, the Ears of the Deaf be unlooſned, the Lame ſhall leap as an Hart, and the Tongue of the Dumb ſhall ſing for Joy,</hi> Iſai. 56, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For the bodies of the riſen believers that are now wrapt up in Diſhonour, ſhall be then cloathed with the higheſt Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> THEN Weakneſs ſhall put on Strength; and that <hi>that is ſown in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhall be raiſed in power,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.43. Then the Coward ſhall be valiant, and the Feeble exceeding ſtrong; their Strength and Courage will be very near Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick then. We read, that an Angel deſtroyed an hundred thouſand in one Night; and how great, ineffably great, will be the Strength and Power of the ſpiritual Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the riſen Saints in that day! But having ſpoke of this diſperſedly afore under other Heads, I ſhall now add no more thereunto; nor mention ſeveral other Advantages that the Bodies of the Saints ſhall ariſe with, that I might inſiſt on: For theſe are ſufficient to evince, that Believers can triumph over the Grave in reſpect of their Bodies.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:97516:15"/>
            <p>THUS having diſpatchd the Doctrinal part. I now proceed to the Application, which I briefly intend to finiſh in three or four Inferences: The two firſt will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly relate to the laſt branch of the Doctrine: The two laſt will reſpect the whole Doctrine in general.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Infer.</hi> THE firſt Inference is, for the Comfort of Believers againſt Death. If it be ſo that their dead Bodies can thus triumph over the Grave, what elſe is there in their Death that ſeems terrible? As for their Souls, they are then inſtantly lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Manſions prepared for them above: But if their Bodies are thus alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently provided for, every thing in Death is to be contemned. Nor need we ſhrink at the Pangs that uſually attend Death; they are but the Cracks of a tatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Houſe, blown up in order to be rebuilt a ſtately Edifice: or rather a Groan or two at farewel, between two parting Friends that have been long loving Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions together, but now muſt be ſeparated for a great ſeaſon, that they might meet again to the greater advantage of both, and theſe are the Body and the Soul. And Death is no leſs to be ſcorned coming by his terrible Meſſengers, Fire, Sword, Gibbets, Poiſon, or the like: When he uſes Inſtruments, he is generally more courteous and gentle in his Dealings, and quicker of diſpatch. A torrid malignant Feaver, or a Torture of ſeveral Weeks or Months by the Stone, Gout, or Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gury, have dealt more cruelly with a Body in diſſolving it, than the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Rack or <hi>Pariſian</hi> Wheel have done. So that conſider Death in all its affrighting Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, it need not be at all frightful to the dying Believer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Infer.</hi> THE ſecond Inference is, for the Comfort of Believers, againſt the tireſome fatigue of Pains, Sickneſſes and Infirmities. The comfortable Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this: That all Pains and Maladies prepare and haſten the Body for the place of refining; as they are Nature's Sufferings, ſo they are the effect of Grace mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the whole Man for Glory: They in whom Grace ſhines moſt, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly moſt infirm in their Bodies; for the Souls that are moſt on the Wing for God, whoſe Graces are moſt vigorous in their Exerciſe, eat out ſooneſt the Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Clay. As the painful feeling of the Body of Death within, is the nailing of the old Man to the Croſs by the new Creature, and Corruption painfully felt and odiouſly ſeen, is Corruption a mortifying; proved by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.5. where he calls the Mortification of Sin, <hi>a being planted into the likeneſs of the Death of Chriſt;</hi> which was a painful and ſhameful, as well as a curſed Death: <hi>v.</hi> 6. he calls it the <hi>crucifixion of the old Man,</hi> and the <hi>deſtruction of the Body of Sin;</hi> that of <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.20, being added thereunto, and compared with <hi>Romans</hi> 7. from the 15 <hi>verſ.</hi> to the end, particularly <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. From all which places, 'tis evident, that the painful feeling of Unbelief, and the Body of Death within is Unbelief and the Body of Death crucified, and the dying Tyger roaring in the Soul. The inward Blows of that Nature we feel, are Stabs at Heart given to inbred Corruption by the ſecond <hi>Adam:</hi> So the pains Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers feel in their Bodies are but as ſo many Blows the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> gives there to the firſt, in order to drive him out, and take up the whole Room for himſelf. Comfort thy ſelf then with theſe words, thou ſick Believer, under thy tedious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady and ſore pains, or with ſuch arguings as theſe: Theſe Pangs indeed are ſharp,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97516:15"/>but they will after yield peaceable and bleſſed fruits, for 'tis in order that that which is earthly may be done away; that that which is ſpiritual may fill up all in all; 'tis for the refining of <hi>Fleſh and Blood;</hi> for Fleſh and Blood, as now circumſtanced, <hi>cannot inherit the Kingdom of God;</hi> neither <hi>Corruption inherit Incorruption,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.50. I will be patient under my greateſt pains then, ſince their tendency is to eat out Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in my Body, ſo that it might inherit eternal Glory, together with my Soul, in incorruption.</p>
            <p>THE other remaining Inferences relate to the whole Doctrine, as laid down in the firſt Sermon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Infer.</hi> THAT the Doctrine is a cogent motive to Holineſs in Life and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Godlineſs in Converſation. If ſo be that a Believer can triumph over Death and the Grave, in reference to his Soul and Body, then the unſpeakably free, rich, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Grace of God in Chriſt manifeſted in him, and believed into, muſt needs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the Man or Woman to all manner of holy Converſation. When Men have ſaid all they can, againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Free Grace,</hi> impiouſly branding it with the Names of Antinomianiſm and Licentiouſneſs; yet this is undeniable from the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the moſt Godly, as well as from the Word of the Lord, that nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains to all manner of holy Obedience, like the Love of Chriſt revealed to the Conſcience, and the Love of the Father in his Love. All that are moſt godly, can ſay what is ſaid of the Woman in the Goſpel; they weep much, and do much, as ſhe, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.44, 47. becauſe they love much; and they love much, becauſe much is frankly forgiven them. This is certain, that the inherent <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the Soul, is the Strength of the Soul, and the Strength or inward Sanctification of the Soul, depends upon looking to, by Faith, that Grace that is in Chriſt. <hi>Thou therefore, my Son, be ſtrong within,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] 2 Tim. 2.1, 5. in the Grace that is in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>viz.</hi> at God's right hand. 'Tis not ſaid, Be ſtrong in the Grace that is in your ſelves, for that is to <hi>ſeek the living among the dead,</hi> a living Chriſt in our dead Frames, when he is never to be found there, for <hi>he is riſen,</hi> and ever lives at the Father's right Hand, to make interceſſion for his Children, and a conſtant ſteady looking to him there, always interceding, and ſtill <hi>full of Grace and Truth;</hi> 'tis that will carry on the Work of Sanctification in the Soul. The ſpiritual Life of a Believer is from Faith, and maintained by Faith. It is written, <hi>The Juſt ſhall live by Faith,</hi> Rom. 1.17. Gal. 3.11. Heb. 10.38. Faith is ſaid to <hi>purifie the Heart,</hi> Acts 15.9. <hi>to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie,</hi> viz. the whole Man, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. and Faith always reſpects Chriſt and his Grace. The <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> i. e. pardoning Grace in the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> received into the Conſcience by believing, is affirmed to <hi>purge the Conſcience from dead Works to ſerve the living God,</hi> Heb. 9.14. The <hi>Grace of God that bringeth Salvation, and hath appeared to all Men</hi> in the Goſpel, but as revealed unto the Conſciences of them that believe, <hi>teacheth them, that denying ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts, they ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent World,</hi> Tit. 2.11, 12. And the GOD of all Grace in manifeſting his Grace to the Soul, that he has called it to eternal Glory by JESUS CHRIST does go on to make perfect, eſtabliſh, ſtrengthen and ſettle the Soul: Which Expreſſions, comprehend all the Work of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in its ſeveral parts and degrees, till it <hi>arrives to the fulneſs of the ſtature of a perfect
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97516:16"/>Man in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> 'Tis apparent from theſe and ſeveral other places of the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that the Grace that is in us, proportionably riſes and falls to the believing Views we have of the Grace that is in the Heart of Chriſt towards us, and in the Hand of Chriſt to give us. To draw towards a cloſe in this matter: This is it I am at, that our inherent Righteouſneſs within us, is begun and carried on by Faith in the imputed Righteouſneſs of Chriſt without us: Theſe two are every way di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, yet ſo as the former ſtill flows from the latter. The All-wiſe GOD has ſo ordered it in the diſpenſation of his Grace, that his free Grace ſhall be magnified, and the Righteouſneſs of his <hi>Son</hi> highly valued and advanced. Were the only uſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Righteouſneſs (and indeed that is a great uſe of it) to ſecure eternal Glory for us, we ſhould be tempted to have little recourſe to it by Faith; for that being once done, and our ſtate ſecured, corrupt Nature would be apt to inſinuate to us there would be no great need of ſuch frequent viewing that God-like Righteouſneſs without us, wherein we ſtand, it being that that is ſo contrary to Fleſh and blood. But now our Holineſs in every ſtep of it depending upon the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt being apprehended by the <hi>Soul</hi> in believing; it muſt, or it ought, to neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate us to have conſtant recourſe, by continued Acts of believing to this glorious Righteouſneſs all the day long. Since it is thus, that every dram of true Goſpel-Holineſs flows into the <hi>Soul</hi> only this way: The Apoſtle affirms it three times, That <hi>now the juſt ſhall live by Faith;</hi> which Life, 'tis evident, he means to be a Life ſpiritual, or Life of Holineſs here. And 'tis neceſſary that the Work of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs be carried on continually and conſtantly; and therefore that we believe in Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs always. The reaſon of all is this: The Lord will have the Righteouſneſs which is of Faith, the imputed Righteouſneſs of his <hi>Son</hi> always view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, believed in, and admired by us. So that hence you may believe the Doctrine of Free-Grace does not tend to Licentiouſneſs (as <hi>Satan</hi> in various Inſtruments clamours againſt it) but the quite contrary. Such undeſerved ſuperabounding Grace to pardoned <hi>Sinners,</hi> being the main motive unto Holineſs of Heart, Lip and Life. The Apoſtle plainly affirms, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. That the <hi>Souls</hi> being brought under Grace, breaks <hi>Sin's</hi> Dominion therein, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Soul being brought in believing under the powerful influence of that <hi>Grace that Reigns through Righteouſneſs unto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, by Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> Rom. 5.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Infer.</hi> The ſecond and laſt uſe is, for the encouragement of Sinners; yea, the chiefeſt, worſt and vileſt to come to Chriſt from the glorious Grace that is held forth in the Doctrine. The Believers, that thus have, and can, triumph over Death and the Grave, were once <hi>Sinners</hi> as you; may be ſome of them as vile as the vileſt of you. Come you, therefore, and taſt and ſee how gracious our Lord the Redeemer is, <hi>Come you and joyn with us in a perpetual Covenant to ſerve the Lord.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the peace of the Goſpel, and make a venture upon an offered Jeſus: Oh come you, the worſt of you, and live the <hi>Life of Faith</hi> like the Juſt, and you ſhall die the Death of the Righteous, to triumph over all in Death. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your Objections can be, this aſtoniſhing Free-Grace can anſwer them all. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom has permitted all along prodigious Mountains of Oppoſition to riſe in the way of Grace, on purpoſe that that Grace of God may declare it ſelf boundleſs
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97516:16"/>by triumphing over all. Thus though it was deſigned from all Eternity, that Free-Grace ſhould have all the Honour in making the Elect happy: Yet a Law for Life was ſet up, that through the Breaches thereof, Sin might be ſuffered to enter; Sin, that odious thing that was ſuch an Affront to the whole Godhead, and brought ſo great an eclipſe on his manifeſtative Glory, was ſuffered, I ſay, to enter, that ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Grace might be magnified in mounting above it. <hi>And the Law entered once again on Mount Sinai, that ſo Sin might abound,</hi> on purpoſe that Free Grace might ſuper-abound, and reign and triumph over all. Free-Grace and electing Love does not only, like <hi>Jordan,</hi> overflow all its Banks, but, like the mighty Deluge, cover the tops of the higheſt Mountains of Oppoſition in the World. Therefore what Objections, O Sinners, can you have againſt bowing down to the Grace offered in the Goſpel. O harden not your Hearts, but <hi>now hear ye his Voice?</hi> Know aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly this, That objecting againſt your acceptance of the Grace of Chriſt (be your Objections never ſo ſpecious) is no other but a gain-ſaying of Chriſt. O do not rebell and gainſay againſt the wide-opened and ſtretcht-forth Arms of eternal Mercy and Compaſſion that now is extended to you. Be thou the vileſt on the face of the Earth, yet as vile as thou has obtained Mercy. There are on Record inſtances of Sovereign Grace, greater than any of you can be: What think you of <hi>Adam?</hi> I durſt almoſt engage to anſwer all thine Objections thou vileſt Sinner, from that ſingle Precedent. You ſay you are the greateſt of Sinners; you cannot be greater than he, who was the Arch-Rebel and Traytor, who led his whole Race into an horrid Rebellion againſt GOD, yet he found Mercy. Ay, but your Sins are great; not greater than his, who, in one Sin, was guilty of the higheſt Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, the moſt monſtrous Unbelief, and the moſt devilliſh Pride and Diſcontent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beſides his breaking the whole Moral Law in that one Sin. Yet you may ſay, My Sins are many. I anſwer, That firſt Sin of his was a pregnant Monſter, millions of Legions in it. But you'll reply, I ſinned againſt Knowledge: So did he, againſt the moſt perfect Knowledge of God and his Will; yes, and againſt the moſt perfect enjoyment of God too; that is more than you can do. But you will object, I have ſinned grievouſly. I reply, <hi>Adam</hi> was reeking hot in his deep-dyed Iniquity, when Mercy ſtepped in. True, ſay you, but I have ſhunned Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: So did he, when he fled to hide himſelf in the Garden. But you may again object, I have extenuated mine heinous Sins, inſtead of abhorring my ſelf for them. Indeed you have done ill; yet though thou haſt done as evil as thou couldſt, yet do not let that diſcourage thee from accepting of offered Mercy; which to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe is the greateſt Sin of all: So did he, and charged God with it too. <hi>The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man thou gaveſt me,</hi> &amp;c. yet he found Mercy; and why not you? Many other things of this nature might be added, but that I am now bound to the greateſt brevity. What ſhall I add, the caſe of <hi>Paul, who was an injurious Perſon, a Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and a Blaſphemer,</hi> yet he obtained Mercy; or the caſe of <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> who had ſeven Devils; of the Woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the Woman mentioned <hi>Luke</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who were all three notorious Sinners, yet Sovereign Grace was extended to them. Let me add but one inſtance more, and that is freſh in your Memories; the caſe of Mr. <hi>Bigg,</hi> whoſe late deceaſe gives the occaſion to this Diſcourſe, and the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97516:17"/>preſent Solemnity. His Death-bed attended with the manifeſtation of ſuch Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty of Grace and Power from above, has allarmed the Neighbourhood. And you ſeem all to be in a ſurprize, and at a gaze about the things you have ſeen and heard relating thereunto: I ſhall therefore give as an exact account of the whole as has come into my Hands, that though he be dead, he may yet ſpeak to you. And though in the Account I ſhall give, it will be neceſſary to touch upon his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Life, yet it ſhall be done with a favourable hand, only ſo much as may tend to the advancement of that glorious Free-Grace manifeſted towards him: But ere I begin, I muſt antidote my Hearers with this Caution; Becauſe it pleaſed the Lord to magnifie his glorious Grace towards him on his Death-bed, that none of you dare to preſume from thence to put of your coming to Chriſt till a Death-bed ſeaſon. The voice of this mighty Providence is, Turn now the worſt of you, and live, 'Tis not, Defer Believing till a dying time. I durſt almoſt venture to ſay, That whoever encourage themſelves to continue in ways of Impenitency from this example, have breaking forth upon them the black Marks and Tokens of final Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. It was well obſerved by one, One Thief on the Croſs, in his dying Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, obtained Grace, that none might deſpair; and but one, that none might preſume: So but one Mr. <hi>Bigg</hi> perhaps in an Age, that none may think when they have lived all their Life-time to Sin, they ſhall with eaſe, and at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, die to Chriſt. Thus having given this Caution, I now proceed to my Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:97516:17"/>
            <head>A NARRATIVE OF Mr. BIGG's CONVERSION, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Bigg,</hi> when married to worthy Mr. <hi>Browning</hi>'s Daughter, was very ſober and well enclined, and by ſome, thought to be Godly. But it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in ſome time after, the Work was but outward; for being led aſide by vain Company, and being at firſt (as it was thought, and he expreſſed it to ſome) filled with dreadful Horrors for it, he fell into a woful Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and continued hardned in Sin, eſpecially that of Company-keeping for ſeveral Years. At laſt he was ſurprized with a lingring Diſtemper, that brought him nigh to the Gates of Death; during which time, he continued ſtupid and unconcerned about his Soul; but it pleaſed the Lord that then he recovered, and continued well for about two years or above; but then fell into a dangerous Relapſe, and then there appeared, pretty early in him, ſome Concernment about his Soul, though he kept it very ſecret, as indeed he was by Nature reſerved, cloſe, and of few Words, except he was amongſt his Company, and diſtempered in his Head. The firſt time he was ſeen to be apparently concerned, was upon this following Occaſion. It has pleaſed the allwiſe God, whoſe ways are in the Deep, and whoſe Judgments are paſt finding out, to lay his heavy Hand upon a Child of his of twelve years of age (who is known to be very gracious) in that ſtrange and unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Diſtemper that hath ſeized many others; which Diſpenſation of God towards us, makes us to be taken up into the Mouths of Talkers, and to be gazed and wondred at by many, who paſs their Cenſures variouſly, as they are diſpoſed. Though we deſire humbly to acquieſs in the Will of the Lord, waiting for his Salvation, not in the leaſt queſtioning, but he will eminently glorifie himſelf in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97516:18"/>the Iſſue, as he has already in ſome Meaſure, bleſſed be his Name, and then they that have reproached us, ſhall ſee, and hear, and be aſhamed. The Diſtemper afflicting the Child with Light-headedneſs (the firſt Effect of it in that kind, as was obſerved on her) ſhe talked of divers things, and amongſt the reſt, of what good People there were in the Neighbourhood that ſhe loved, and amongſt the reſt, ſhe ſaid her Mother was good and would go to Heaven; but being asked concerning her Father, whether ſhe thought her Father would go to Heaven; ſhe replied, ſhe deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he might: Hereupon Mr. <hi>Bigg</hi> being called, and ſhe again in his Preſence ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what ſhe ſaid of her Father? Nothing, ſays the Child, very gravely and aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, but that I wiſh his eternal Good? which Words fell upon him with ſuch Power and Weight, that it caſt him into great Paſſion of Weeping for ſome time. About that time, being very reſtleſs in the Night, ſaid to his dear Relation, he needed to have ſomething: It was anſwered (ſuppoſing he meant Phyſick) that nothing would do him more good than a little Sleep. He replied, yes, a little Hope would do me more good. It was told him, True! a little good Hope through Grace, would do you more good indeed. Remember that Place of Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.22. <hi>Look unto me and be ſaved, all the ends of the Earth? For I am God, and there is none elſe.</hi> He preſently anſwered, That was not ſo eaſily done, and then continued, Theſe Words have run in my Mind of late to terrifie me: <hi>Becauſe I have called, and you have refuſed,</hi> &amp;c. And many dreadful Scriptures alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Then he was told, That Chriſt was able to ſave to the uttermoſt. Yes, ſaid he, and able to deſtroy to the uttermoſt too. Then he ended (ſpeaking nothing of Soul Matters, but what the Force of Terror one while, and Joy another while made him. Some time after he was again complaining; which, whilſt he was doing, he was acquainted, That his Condition was hopeful though painful: It being added, Time was, when you have been under God's Hand, and in great Danger, and to my Apprehenſion, was ſtupid and Sottiſh. He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Yes, it was ſo. Then being asked, if he had not ſome Hope, he replied, that ſometimes he was ready to think, that if God had had a Purpoſe to deſtroy him, he would have done it before now. Not long after, as he was going to Bed one Night, he asked one, what ſhe thought of him, as to his Living? ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, ſhe did not know what the Lord would do with him: As to Senſe, you are not like to be long in this World (he then being very weak.) And muſt I die then? ſaid he: Oh, I dare not die! I dare not die! Oh! 'tis an awful thing to die, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some ſhort time after, whilſt he was in his bitter Complaints, ſeveral Scriptures were laid afore him to encourage his Believing into Chriſt. He ſaid, right! if it had been in time; but it is too late now. He was anſwered, it was not too late, ſeeing the Lord had opened his Eyes on this ſide of the Grave, and made him ſee his Need of Chriſt. He ſaid, yes, it is too late; for I have had the prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of Chriſt, and the ſame Tenders of Salvation with others: And I would not have Chriſt then, and therefore it is juſt with God to deny him to me now. But one added, you can juſtifie God under all. Oh! Ay, ſaid he: Oh! Ay. He that hath born ſo many years Provocations at my Hands — I will ſpeak well of him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> long as I live, however he deals with me. Another time he deſired that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97516:18"/>might be turned to, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. <hi>That I may apprehend that, for which alſo I am apprehended of Chriſt.</hi> Methinks, ſaid he, it bears this Senſe: That Chriſt muſt firſt take hold of the Soul, before the Soul can take hold of Chriſt. A little before he kept his Bed, he ſaid to his Wife: Dear, What muſt I do? There is no way for me but to cloſe with Jeſus Chriſt, and I cannot do it, I cannot do it. I do not know either whether I am willing to be ſaved by Chriſt or no. May be, if I ſhould recover, things would wear off. Oh! I dread the Thoughts of it. If I may but live till I have obtained Mercy, I ſhall think I have lived long enough. But Oh! the Thoughts how few find Mercy at laſt, would make any ones Heart to ake. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Heart of his dear Relation to ſend to the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Rothwell,</hi> to pray for him, acquainted him with it; asking him, if it was not his Deſire alſo. He anſwered, he thought of it ſome Days afore, but durſt not be ſo bold as to mention ſuch a thing; but did deſire they ſhould ſeek the Lord for him, that he might cloſe ſaveingly with Jeſus Chriſt, and have a true Godly Sorrow and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, never to be repented of. Now we are drawing towards the Cloſe of his Life. The <hi>Friday</hi> before he departed, he could ſcarce riſe, being exceeding weak; but he began to be very earneſt about his Soul. He ſpake thus to Mrs. <hi>Bigg,</hi> The Prayers of God's People are a great ſupport to me; I always had a great Eſteem of the Prayers of God's People. That Night he was confined to his Bed; when he was laid in it, he ſaid very awfully, I ſhall riſe no more till the Trumpet ſounds. When in Bed, he was complaining of the greatneſs of his Sins; he was taken up by one, ſaying, Whether he thought his Sins ſo great, as that there was not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in Chriſt to pardon? No, ſays he, I will not reflect ſuch Diſhonour on the Blood of Chriſt, as to think ſo. I know there is an effectual Plaiſter prepared; but if not applied, what then? A little after he brake forth into this Expreſſion: As there is a fulneſs of ſin in me, ſo there is much more Fulneſs in Chriſt to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. However that Night he continued very reſtleſs, his Diſtreſs being ſuch, he could ſcarcely lay his Eyes together: And in the Morning (which was <hi>Saturday</hi>) he ſpoke in great Agony, I muſt die, and have not the leaſt bit of Hope. Being then adviſed to venture on Chriſt, and caſt himſelf upon him, as one able to ſave to the uttermoſt: He with a Countenance, that witneſſed huge inward Grief, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, it was too late. His dear Relation anſwered him thus, It is not too late. God has opened your Eyes on this ſide the Grave, and made you ſee your need of Chriſt; therefore 'tis not too late; but he calleth you now. He preſently ſpake thus, Shall I venture then upon Chriſt? It was anſwered him, He muſt. Then having pauſed, his Countenance more compoſed and cheary, he ſpake reſolvedly, I can but periſh—then ſtopped. Then his dear Wife ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his Words and countenance, ſaid, Hope is a Dawning. He quickly replied, I hope it is, and ſoon after burſt forth into high Acclamations and Expreſſions of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Joy, and Admirations of the free Grace of God as Strength would permit. But he was much afflicted, that he had not Strength nor Breath to ſpeak of God's free Grace to him, that the World might know what God had done for him. Notwithſtanding he ſpake ſomewhat to this effect: It troubles me that God ſhould looſe his Glory, who hath not, I hope, ſuffered me to looſe my Soul. Oh, that I had Breath to ſpeak of Chriſt! Methinks I could ſpeak of Chriſt till Night! I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97516:19"/>think I could ſpeak of Chriſt a Year together! And indeed all that Day, when he had ſtrength to ſpeak, it was excellently of Chriſt: And once fetching his Breath with much Difficulty, he ſaid, I ſhall breath out my laſt Breath with a bleſſed be God for Jeſus Chriſt; and little afterwards he would complain, that he could love Chriſt no more. That day there came a young Gentleman, an Acquantance of his, to viſit him, who found him very weak; but when he had recovered a little Strength, he addreſſed himſelf to him thus: All that we have to do for God and our Souls Salvation, is to be done here: There is nothing to be done in the Grave, and it is my Advice, and my dying Counſel to all young Men, that they labour to make ſure of Chriſt in a time of Health, and not put off ſo great a Work as I have done.</p>
            <p>The following Day, which was the Lords Day, he was exceeding weak, and pained in his Body, and variouſly exerciſed in his Soul, as appears by ſeveral Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions that dropt from him at times. Whilſt he was complaining of his Illneſs, he was told, that however it was, yet God is good, He anſwered, You ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hear me ſay otherwiſe, ſink or ſwim, ſaved or damned, I will juſtifie him. A little after, being exerciſed in his Soul, he cryed out, How hard a thing it is to croud through the Throng of Sin and Guilt to Jeſus Chriſt: Sure Chriſt will not accept of ſuch a filthy thing as I: But, ſaid he again, God's End in pardoning and ſaving Sinners, is to glorifie his own free Grace; and then why not towards me as well as another? What a wonderful Word is that? A Man may die with that Word in his Mouth, <hi>The free Gift is of many Offences unto Juſtification.</hi> Then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, And though my Fleſh and my Heart faileth, <hi>God is the Strength of my Heart, and my Portion for ever.</hi> Another time, being ſomewhat clouded, and ſpeaking of the Grace of God, I cannot demand it, nor have I deſerved it: But being asked, if he would not accept of it: Yes, reply'd he, very thankfully. Towards Night he grew more diſtreſſed, for ſeveral Friends being gathered about him he looked upon them dolefully, and ſaid, Oh, I tremble! being asked at what? he anſwered, at the poſſibility of Periſhing. One then ſitting by, that knew how it was with him, told him, it was impoſſible, he being helped through Grace to commit his Soul into ſuch Hands. It was ſaid further, <hi>None can pull you out of his Hands.</hi> He ſpeaks a little after, Poor Hearts, you are willing to hope the beſt; I wiſh you are not miſtaken. You know, ſaid he, to his Wife, Dear, oppreſſed Nature will cry out for Relief; but being anſwered, that oppreſſed Nature could not reſt on Chriſt for Salvation; or to this Effect, he was ſilent. Next Morning he was much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining that he was to die, and do Chriſt no Service in the World. He cryed out, Oh, that I might live but one Year! but may be if I ſhould, I would be wicked: But yet, ſaid he, I think verily, if I know my Heart, I am willing to imbrace Chriſt on his own Terms; I think verily, if I was to live the ſtricteſt Life as ever Saint lived, yet I think I could embrace none but Chriſt. A little after, being full of Complaints as to his Soul, it was told him, Yeſterday you could ſay, though my Heart and my Fleſh faileth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He anſwered, But I cannot ſay ſo to day. Some time after, his Faith began to mount up, and being melted under the Sence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God's Grace to him, he ſaid, If I had ſtrength, I would ſoon make my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97516:19"/>Town-Talk. I need not tell the Town what my Life hath been; they know that very well: But I would have them know the difference between them that have Grace, and them that have none. <hi>Monday</hi> about Noon Mr. <hi>Bear</hi> came to viſit him, and asked him, What, art thee going now to Chriſt? He anſwered, Better now than ever. But he was ſo weak, and laboured with ſuch Difficulty of Breathing, that he could ſcarce ſpeak; which he expreſſed himſelf, ſaying, That if it were to ſave his Life, he could not ſpeak; yet deſired Mr. <hi>Bear,</hi> that he would wreſtle and ſtrive with God in Prayer for him, that he might be helped ſincerely to cloſe with Chriſt. A little after, finding his Weakneſs increaſe upon him, he ſpake thus, I am brought to the Duſt of Death. That Night, which was the Night before he departed, about nine a Clock, he grew weaker and weaker, and fetch'd his Breath ſhorter and ſhorter: Being a little lifted up on his Pillow, he lifted up his Hands, and bad all farewell. After which, he drew his Breath as one juſt departing; being (as 'twas thought) paſt ſpeaking, was ſpoke to by a Friend thus, putting him in mind of his own Expreſſion, Bleſſed be God for Jeſus Chriſt; whereat he was heard to ſay ſoftly, <hi>Amen.</hi> Then his dear Relation added, Chriſt the Fore-runner is for thee entred: Then he, with a pleaſant Countenance, nodded his Head, being not able to ſpeak. And now Death indeed was in his Face in all its Symptoms, and all concluded him juſt a dying; when, all of a ſuddain, his Blood returned into his Face, Vigor and livelineſs into his opened Eyes, and with a Voice exceeding loud, as if he had roſe from the Dead on purpoſe to give in his dying Teſtimony for free Grace, he thus ſpake triumphantly. I know that my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer liveth, and that with theſe Eyes I ſhall ſee him, and not anothers: <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly; Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly; Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly:</hi> Theſe Words he ſpake with ſuch Vehemence, that he made the whole Houſe to eccho, when afore he could ſcarce be heard if one laid his Ear to his Mouth, and then continued thus with no leſs Accent and Affection, I am no more afraid to die, than I am to ſhut my Eyes: I am no more afraid to die, than I am to go to ſleep. God loves me dearly, and I love God dearly: I am ſure he will do me no hurt. Lord, ſtrike the Blow, and the Work is done, I long to be gone, I long to ſee Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. O that all the Town might ring of God's free Grace to me! What, at the laſt Hour too? Who would have thought of this a few Weeks ago? Nothing leſs than Eternity is ſufficient to admire free Grace: This is bleſſed Work indeed: This is Dying indeed. Thy Father, ſaid he, turning to his Wife, will wonder to ſee me in Heaven: He little thinks I am ſo near him. His Wife asked him, if he thought ſhe ſhould ever come where he was a going. He anſwered, I do not queſtion it; thou, nor the poor Children neither. Through God's Grace, his dying Propheſie is in a likely way to be accompliſhed in all of them.) You will not be long after me. Come, one Boſom will hold us all: He that hath begun the good Work in them (meaning his Children) will carry it on till the Day of Jeſus Chriſt. A Friend hearing him ſpeak ſo heartily, ſaid, Sir, I hope you may live ſtill. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied. Oh do not tell me ſo! I do not love to hear of that Ear: I would not come back again for thouſands of Gold and Silver; but what the Lord will, I am whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97516:20"/>ſwallowed up in Gods Soveraign will. After he was ſpent with ſpeaking, he ſaid, I can ſpeak no more; I hope you are all ſatisfied. Fare you well, expecting (as it ſeems) he ſhould have gone immediately to Heaven. But it pleaſed the Lord to order it otherwiſe, and to continue him till the next Night, though under ſome Regret, for he preſently added, Oh! I thought I had been going ſo ſweetly, but I am here ſtill; and next Morning, hearing ſome Friends diſcourſing about the Diſtreſs he had been in, he ſaid to them, but the Lord has now fully ſatisfied me. Yet by reaſon his Diſſolution was delayed, it occaſioned further Temptation, and a black Cloud aroſe upon his Soul after all this glorious Sun-ſhine. He burſt out into ſuch bitter Expreſſions as theſe: God has forſaken me, and I am afraid 'tis a ſore Judgment of God upon me, that I lye in ſuch a Condition. I am afraid, leaſt I have deceived my ſelf with falſe Hopes. Some time after the beginning of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, there appeared on him Convulſive Fits; whereupon he ſaid to his Wife, I have Fits. She anſwered, I am afraid you have. He added, I am almoſt fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of my Wits. Being asked at what: He replied, At the Awfulneſs of Death. This Conflict laſted for ſome time; but the Lord was pleaſed to return again, as was perceived; for his Soul was compoſed and ſtill. His Fits ceaſed, though his Strength was gone, that he could ſpeak but litttle. However, this for Satisfaction was had from him a little before he departed. He ſaid, would I was up! His Wife anſwered, That would be a pleaſant Sight indeed to ſee thee up again, to tell us what thou haſt ſeen on this ſick Bed. He anſwered, I have ſeen that here, which hath made my Heart, and the Hearts of many more glad. It was then told him, you may ſee now what Satan's Temptations are, when God permits him, he will rob a Child of God of his Comforts; but that is all he can do. And it is a great All too, ſaid he, it was that which made my Life a Burthen to me. Being asked, if he did not believe he ſhould have Comfort again. He anſwered, Yes, but did not know when. But it was not long before he had it to the full; for now he fell into a ſweet Sleep, the beſt he had for many Days; in which Sleep, he quietly ſlept in Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Thus I have given you an Account of ſome of his Death bed Experiences, in whom; though now dead, he yet ſpeaketh to you the Living, and invites you all to partake of the ſame Grace with him, that you may enter into the ſame Glory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e now is in. Have a care, as I cautioned you afore, to ſuck Poiſon to the Ruine of your own Souls out of this Inſtance of God's Free, Rich, and Glorious Grace; but make this Improvement of it, to ſtir you up now to accept of, and venture on the boundleſs Grace of God in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Conſider what has been ſaid, and the Lord give you <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="epitaph">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97516:20"/>
               <head>His EPITAPH.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here lies interred</l>
                  <l>The Body of Mr. <hi>John Bigg;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who departed this Mortal Life,</l>
                  <l>When he had ſeen his thirty ſeventh Year,</l>
                  <l>On the twenty eighth Day of <hi>January,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Anno Domini, 1689.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Cropt in his full blown Age, if we by Grace</l>
                  <l>His time compute, he liv'd but five Weeks ſpace.</l>
                  <l>Dead whilſt alive, in dying Life begins.</l>
                  <l>Short Race of Life! But what a Crown he wins!</l>
                  <l>In Sin him Death attacks; but Grace ſteps in,</l>
                  <l>And makes him Triumph over Death and Sin.</l>
                  <l>Thus by Chriſt's Death, in death he's made to cry;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Death, where's thy Sting? Grave, where's thy Victory?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Now to the only wiſe God be Glory and Dominion World without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
